中文字幕
[MUSIC - FERGIE & Q TIP & GOONROCK, "A LITTLE PARTY NEVER KILLED NOBODY"]
FERGIE & Q-TIP & GOONROCK: (SINGING) Just one night,
中文字幕
all we got, just one nigh, all we got, just one night, all we
got, just one night, all we got.
中文字幕
A little party never killed nobody.
So we going to dance until we drop, drop, drop.
中文字幕
Mm, a little party never killed nobody.
Right here, right now, is all we got. skeeten-bod-op-bop.
中文字幕
[MUSIC - FERGIE & Q TIP &
GOONROCK, "A LITTLE PARTY NEVER KILLED NOBODY"]
中文字幕
(SINGING) A little party never killed nobody.
So we're going to dance until we drop.
中文字幕
Let's go.
A little party never killed nobody.
中文字幕
Right here, right now is all we got.
Oh, a little party never killed nobody.
中文字幕
So we're going to dance until we drop.
A little party never killed nobody.
中文字幕
[MUSIC - FERGIE & Q TIP &
GOONROCK, "A LITTLE PARTY NEVER KILLED NOBODY"]
中文字幕
MUPPET: [SNORING]
All right.
中文字幕
This is CS50, and this is lecture 8.
And that was a look at the so-called CS50 hackathon, this annual tradition
中文字幕
with which we nearly end the semester that will start around 7:00 PM here
in Cambridge, will then end around 7:00 AM the next day in Cambridge.
中文字幕
And punctuating the evening will be quite a bit of work
on final projects, which is the overarching goal of the evening
中文字幕
to give students, both an academic and a very
social and collaborative environment in which to tackle
中文字幕
their final achievements in the course.
But also, as you gleaned there will be a bit of distraction, a bit of food
中文字幕
from Felipe's, typically, around 9:00 PM, a little bit of Domino's Pizza
around 1:00 AM.
中文字幕
And for those still standing as in the muppet there,
we'll treat you to breakfast at IHOP if you still have the energy.
中文字幕
Thereafter, we'll be the so-called CS50 Fair, the climax of everything
that you've done in CS50.
中文字幕
And more on that in the weeks to come.
So without further ado, where have we been these past several weeks?
中文字幕
Well, recall that, over the past couple of weeks,
we've been introducing web programming.
中文字幕
And most recently, did we try to tie together a lot of the topics
from the past few weeks.
中文字幕
HTML and CSS and JavaScript, and then Python, and then another framework,
another piece of software called Flask that
中文字幕
just made it easier and more possible to build web-based applications.
And the simplest example of that last week, recall,
中文字幕
looked a little something like this.
And this past week with the problems on similarities and survey,
中文字幕
have you been building your own web-based applications.
But they haven't quite had all of the pieces
中文字幕
that you might want to assemble into a web-based app.
And so today, we'll fill in those final blanks.
中文字幕
But recall that we've been trying to frame these applications, not
as one-offs or just tools that you built, but as part
中文字幕
of a common paradigm or a methodology.
And indeed, when you're learning computer science and software
中文字幕
engineering, you start to notice patterns in the software,
in the code that you're writing.
中文字幕
And humans tend to adopt these patterns because they save you time.
And then everyone can speak the same language, so to speak.
中文字幕
So MVC was the acronym we introduced last week, Model View Controller.
And that just speaks to this paradigm whereby
中文字幕
you organized certain type of code in one file, certain types of other code
and another file.
中文字幕
So your Python code goes in application.py.
Your HTML goes in your HTML files, your CSS in your CSS files, and so forth.
中文字幕
But what we didn't have last week was this thing here, really.
Model generally refers to your data.
中文字幕
And while survey, your most recent problem,
did have data, a CSV file that's arguably a model,
中文字幕
CSV is not terribly expressive.
You can pretty much just write rows to a text file, not unlike a spreadsheet.
中文字幕
But you can't really query it.
You can't easily insert or delete.
中文字幕
You pretty much would have to reconstruct the whole file.
And indeed, that's exactly what I did back in the day.
中文字幕
The very first web-based application I wrote back in sophomore or junior year
was the freshman intramural website.
中文字幕
And all I had available to me, both technologically and conceptually,
we're CSV files.
中文字幕
I had no idea what databases were, didn't realize how much easier they
could make my life.
中文字幕
So I stored all of the data behind these links here just
in very simple text files.
中文字幕
But today, will give you so much more power.
And especially, if you're coming into the class with an interest
中文字幕
in applying CS to other fields in medicine or the arts
or any world in which there's data, particularly,
中文字幕
in STEM and data science and the like, realize
that SQL has really become this incredibly powerful language
中文字幕
with which to solve problems in those and so many domains.
And ultimately, what your build, this coming week--
中文字幕
your very last CS50 problem set--
you have now peaked just about-- will be CD50
中文字幕
Finance, a web-based application by which you can buy,
or "buy" and sell stocks.
中文字幕
And so what you're going to do this coming week is write code
that implements a web application that resembles this whereby
中文字幕
your users and yourself will be able to register for an account,
log into that account.
中文字幕
You'll be given for free, thanks to us, 10,000 virtual dollars.
And then you can go ahead and buy and sell stocks via their symbol
中文字幕
using this application.
So for instance, if I go ahead and register myself here.
中文字幕
Let's say, username Malan, password 12345--
shouldn't have said that.
中文字幕
Go ahead and register here.
You'll see that, by default, I get this free $10,000 in virtual cash.
中文字幕
You know what, I'm going to go ahead and buy myself
a share of maybe Netflix, whose symbol is NFLX.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and try to buy one share.
Voila.
中文字幕
And now you'll see that, not only do I have less cash left, about $9,600,
I now own a share of stock.
中文字幕
And if we reload this throughout the lecture, frankly,
the price might go a little up or a little down
中文字幕
because this web application you'll build
will also talk to an API, an Application Programming Interface--
中文字幕
so some third-party website that provides you with stock data.
So you ask it for the current price of a stock.
中文字幕
It gives you an answer in JSON format, if you
recall our short discussion of that.
中文字幕
And you'll integrate it, ultimately, into this interface.
So this will be the culmination of so many of the ideas
中文字幕
and the building blocks with which you've experimented.
But we need a few final pieces today.
中文字幕
So first and foremost, when I registered for this site, I created an account.
And indeed, I can go ahead and log out now.
中文字幕
And if I go ahead and log back in--
if no one's stolen my password yet, I can see my account and only my account.
中文字幕
But we haven't yet seen any mechanism in code
whereby you can implement this notion of logging in, right?
中文字幕
What is the underlying logic via which a website knows that you are logged in
or you're not logged in, right?
中文字幕
Clearly, when I went to this website just a moment ago,
it prompted me to log in because I was not because I had logged out.
中文字幕
But how did it know that?
And now that I am logged in, how does it know that I can click on "quote"
中文字幕
to get just the stock quote or "buy" just to buy a stock or "sell."
Why does it not prompt me every time I click a link to log back
中文字幕
in with my username or password?
What do you think?
中文字幕
Isn't cookies little files that
saves the data inside your browser's cache that let it know what's going on.
中文字幕
Yeah, cookies--
little files that get saved by websites on your computer.
中文字幕
Now odds are, most everyone here has probably heard in some form,
cookies-- bad.
中文字幕
Maybe bad, privacy-invading, yes?
OK.
中文字幕
So true.
But most of the web would not work without them.
中文字幕
So someone else, what do you understand a cookie to be?
What is a cookie?
中文字幕
Basically saves your information
so you don't have to put it in every time.
中文字幕
Yeah.
It saves your information so you don't have to put it in every time.
中文字幕
So in simplest form, it's exactly a combination of those answers.
Whereby, when I log into a website, you could
中文字幕
imagine that website just remembering my username and my password
by just saving them in a little file on my Mac or PC
中文字幕
so that the next time I visit a web page,
it just automatically sends them for me, so that the human doesn't
中文字幕
have to type them again and again.
Now let's find fault with that.
中文字幕
Feels like that would work, but what's a downside of that naive implementation?
What do you think instinctively?
中文字幕
The data is just out there?
The data is just out there, right?
中文字幕
I have people in the office or at home or in a library
that I might not want to just be able to walk up to that computer
中文字幕
and just see this little text file planted on my computer.
Because then they could log in to my account by just digging around.
中文字幕
So it feels a little invasive.
Indeed, that's one of the threats of cookies.
中文字幕
So it turns out cookies or websites tend not to do that, at least,
if they're implemented well.
中文字幕
They instead just plant a really big random number on your hard drive
or in your computer's ram or memory.
中文字幕
So 1234567-- like, some really big number maybe with letters and numbers
maybe even some punctuation that uniquely identifies me.
中文字幕
And thereafter, any time I click a link on that same website,
after logging in, my browser, thanks to HTTP--
中文字幕
the language that browsers and servers speak that we discussed a few weeks
back--
中文字幕
just magically sends that same big random number
to the server again and again.
中文字幕
And so long as the server remembers that that big random number corresponds
to user name Malan, it can figure out whose account to show.
中文字幕
And why is it a big random number?
Why is it not just my password or my username?
中文字幕
Why am I proposing that it be a big random number?
Sometimes people can guess it by just using a random generator.
中文字幕
Exactly.
In computer science, randomness is this incredibly powerful ingredient.
中文字幕
If you pick a big enough word or a big enough string
or sentence, the probability that some random adversary, or bad person
中文字幕
on the internet, is going to be able to guess or try
to guess that value is just so low, it's just not realistically
中文字幕
ever going to happen in your lifetime statistically.
And so random this gives us that capability.
中文字幕
And so you can think about this metaphorically in the real world
as being like a hand stamp.
中文字幕
If you've ever gone to an amusement park or a bar
or a club where you have to show your ID or you
中文字幕
have to pay for a ticket on the way in, sometimes they'll
stamp you with either visible or invisible ink.
中文字幕
And that's largely for efficiency so that, thereafter,
when you're in the amusement park, you can come and go.
中文字幕
And you don't have to repay or reprocess.
If you're in the bar or the club, you don't have to keep showing your ID.
中文字幕
They can check once, and then more efficiently let you come and go
as you please.
中文字幕
Because you're just presenting your hand or this virtual hand
stamp to the bouncer or to the gatekeeper at those places.
中文字幕
So cookies are exactly like that.
Unbeknownst to us all this time, anytime you visit a website into which you've
中文字幕
logged in, your browser is secretly but usefully
presenting a hand stamp to that server to remind it who you are.
中文字幕
Or rather, not really who you are, but of that big random number
so that, if the server remembers who that number belongs to,
中文字幕
it can figure out whose account to then show.
So put more concretely, if I actually pull up some of the HTTP examples
中文字幕
that we looked at in the past, let's consider this in context.
So almost everyone here has probably used Gmail at some point.
中文字幕
And you log in generally via page like this.
So it might be infrequent because you're not often
中文字幕
prompted to log into email because of-- surprise, surprise-- cookies
from Google being on your computer.
中文字幕
But let's see where those come from.
So when you request Google or gmail.com, you might send, in a virtual envelope,
中文字幕
so to speak, from your Mac or PC to the server, a message like this.
Families who've not seen this before, this
中文字幕
is what your browser is actually sending to a server in order
to request a home page of gmail.com.
中文字幕
Now, I'm going to simplify this a little bit
because there's a bunch of redirects--
中文字幕
HTTP 302s and 301's involved that aren't that interesting today.
So let's just assume that Gmail responds immediately.
中文字幕
Typically, Gmail would respond with this, saying 200 OK.
Here's the login page.
中文字幕
And here's a web page in text/html format.
But once you've logged in, what your Gmail actually does
中文字幕
is it also sends this.
Recall that we call these things HTTP headers--
中文字幕
key value pairs separated by colons that are semi-secretly sent from browser
to server and from server to browser.
中文字幕
Now we, more sophisticated developer types can see this stuff, right?
You can open up Chrome's network tab and start poking around.
中文字幕
And it's not secret per se.
It's just most people don't know it's there.
中文字幕
And what Google and other companies are doing is
they literally send a header called set-cookie, the value of which
中文字幕
is that big random value that the server has decided for you.
Your browser, assuming that it speaks HTTP properly,
中文字幕
should then save that value in RAM, your computer's memory,
or on your hard drive.
中文字幕
And then, every other click you make on gmail.com should send,
not just headers like this, but it should send the opposite header--
中文字幕
just cookie, not set-cookie, but cookie, which
is the presentation of that hand stamp.
中文字幕
And so every time you click a page on Gmail, or Facebook,
or almost any website into which you've logged in.
中文字幕
Those cookies have been planted on your computer.
Now recently, in both Europe and in the US,
中文字幕
have laws been passed that are increasingly putting pressure
on companies that operate internationally to present you
中文字幕
with cookie-based information, right?
You get these little pop-ups increasingly.
中文字幕
And you've been getting them for years in Europe saying,
can we plant cookies on your computer?
中文字幕
So given all of this, what might happen if you say
no, no cookies on my computer?
中文字幕
You have to keep logging in.
You're going to have to keep logging in, right?
中文字幕
If you take away this fundamental HTTP feature, much of the web
breaks, or the user experience deteriorates significantly.
中文字幕
Now the flip side is cookies can be used, not only for good, so to speak,
but also for evil.
中文字幕
It turns out that there are a lot of ads on the internet, of course.
And that's what drives a lot of the revenue that makes it all possible.
中文字幕
Those ads typically come from image tags in your HTML or script tags
or some of the HTML tags we have seen in the class.
中文字幕
But they go to third-party servers, somewhereelse.com.
And the problem arises with cookies when those third parties are allowed
中文字幕
to plant cookies on your computer.
Because if you go to Google, and you go to Facebook,
中文字幕
and you go to Twitter-- bunches of websites.
Suppose they all have some middlemen advertising service advertising
中文字幕
on each of these websites.
That middlemen, so to speak, because they
中文字幕
have their ads and, therefore, their HTTP headers on this site,
and this site, and this site, there are big third parties
中文字幕
out there-- lots of them advertising networks-- that know everywhere
little old you is going because they see your cookie appearing
中文字幕
from multiple different other sites.
And so here's where cookies become, not a computer science, engineering feat,
中文字幕
but really a threat to one's privacy because they
can be used so easily for tracking.
中文字幕
And frankly, AT&T and Verizon, as an aside, got into trouble--
not enough people know this--
中文字幕
some years back when they started injecting, forcibly, additional HTTP
headers similar in spirit to this to all of people's cell phone traffic--
中文字幕
so not things you could even opt out of initially.
Because this was a way for advertisers and for themselves
中文字幕
to be able to track users.
So these HTTP headers on which cookies are based
中文字幕
are very powerful, but also very invasive.
And we're only now starting to see, societally and politically,
中文字幕
pushback on this very simple mechanism that, hopefully, we as CS types
just understand the mechanics of and, therefore, now the implications.
中文字幕
So let's see this in context, for instance.
Let me go ahead and open up a relatively small example in CS50 IDE.
中文字幕
For those unfamiliar, CS50 IDE is a web-based application
via which you can write programs in the cloud,
中文字幕
just using any browser on a Mac or PC.
I'm going to go ahead into my account here.
中文字幕
And I'm going to go into Store.
And I'm going to go into the Templates directory
中文字幕
and show that this example here has a few files.
This will look familiar to students in the room.
中文字幕
Application.py is the web-based application.
And then we have some template files, so to speak.
中文字幕
In my Terminal window here, I'm going to go ahead and, with just my keyboard,
go into this directory called Store in source 8, which is available online.
中文字幕
And I'm going to go ahead and do a flask run, which, for those unfamiliar,
is the command via which you can start a web server
中文字幕
and start running a web-based application.
So now that I have that, I'm going to go ahead and visit exactly this URL here.
中文字幕
And we'll see a relatively simple and super ugly web store.
Let me go ahead and zoom in a bit.
中文字幕
And this web store allows me to buy three things-- foos, bars,
and bazes, whatever those are.
中文字幕
And this is a very simple e-commerce-like site
where I just have to type the quantity of foos, bars, and bazes that I want.
中文字幕
And then I can go ahead and buy them.
So I'm going to go ahead and say, give me one foo, how about zero bars,
中文字幕
and these two bazes.
And I'm going to go ahead and click Purchase.
中文字幕
And now you'll see my shopping cart.
But if I continue shopping, you'll see that it
中文字幕
resets, just like if you keep browsing Amazon or whatever other website.
But if you want to check shopping cart again,
中文字幕
notice it's remembered what I'm looking for.
And in fact, you know what?
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and close the window.
Oops.
中文字幕
I actually lost the website.
But you know what?
中文字幕
If I go back to that URL and reopen, I see the storefront.
But if I view my shopping cart, it has remembered my state.
中文字幕
So notice the power now of cookies.
It's not just to remember with a hand stamp who you are.
中文字幕
But now you can remember anything about that user that you want, right?
A shopping cart on Amazon or any website is the best example of this
中文字幕
because it would be horrible, horrible, horrible for a User Experience or UX
if every time you click the darn link, you
中文字幕
lost the contents of your shopping cart because the website forgot who you are.
So this is a compelling feature to remember.
中文字幕
And it's cookies that implement this feature too.
Because more generally, what's going on with cookies is this.
中文字幕
When you set a cookie using the set-cookie header that
looked like this, there is a key value pair
中文字幕
to the right that we might call session, and that has the value.
Value is the hand stamp.
中文字幕
Session is just a term of art that refers to this abstraction
that you can think of really as a shopping cart.
中文字幕
But it doesn't have to have anything to do with actual shopping or e-commerce.
It's just a container in which you can store stuff.
中文字幕
So this is telling the website that my session value, my hand stamp
is 12345-- and big really random number.
中文字幕
The website can then say, you know what?
I'm going to store a container for you.
中文字幕
Let's call it a Python dictionary, or dict for you,
inside of which I can put anything I want.
中文字幕
And so in fact, when you go to a shopping cart like this,
what is the server actually doing?
中文字幕
Well, upon seeing your hand stamp, and realizing, oh, you are user 1234567.
Oh, that's username Malan.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and grab the dictionary, the Python dict
from memory, or even from a CSV file if you want,
中文字幕
and show you the contents of your shopping cart.
Meanwhile, someone else, Brian visits the same exact website
中文字幕
and logs in with his account.
He's going to present a different hand stamp, presumably.
中文字幕
And so the website can look for a different dictionary
and show Brian the different contents of his shopping cart.
中文字幕
And the same for everyone in this room.
So this simple mechanism--
中文字幕
I mean, consider the power.
This is just a stupid text value key:value.
中文字幕
And from all of that does all of the web's capabilities now come.
And we won't look in too much detail into the code here,
中文字幕
but let me show one snippet of it.
If I go into application.py, the magic that makes this possible in flask
中文字幕
is just to import this additional feature.
You'll recall, from the past couple of problems
中文字幕
you've worked on, you import from flask a few things--
render template, redirect, request.
中文字幕
Well, if you Add session to that list, which
is the code abstraction of this hand-stamp idea, what you can now do
中文字幕
is this.
Let me scroll down to the juicy part here.
中文字幕
And notice that you can do lines of code now,
and for the next CS50 finance problem, lines of code like this.
中文字幕
Session is just a Python dictionary, or dict.
You can index into it using any word--
中文字幕
foo, or bar, or baz, just like you could with dictionaries more generally.
And you can store in it anything you want.
中文字幕
In my case, I want to store a number--
0 foos, or 1 foo, or 2 foos or whatever.
中文字幕
So I can simply convert to an int, the user's request forms
item, whatever that is.
中文字幕
And let me wave my hand at some of the code above because it just
sets the whole thing up.
中文字幕
But the new line of code, the new feature
that now will empower us to build something like a stock trading website
中文字幕
is quite simply this line here.
Because what you can also do to remember that a user is logged in,
中文字幕
just go ahead and store in this so-called session,
a value of, like, true.
中文字幕
And if the value true is there, you can infer that the human is logged in.
And if there's no such value in the dictionary, they are not logged in.
中文字幕
And so we'll hold your hand a bit more in the next problem set
with this introduction of CS50 Finance.
中文字幕
And we'll write some of the code that handles the login,
so you can see by example how to do this.
中文字幕
But it'll be up to you thereafter to start
remembering what stocks a user actually has
中文字幕
using sessions to retain the fact that they've logged in already.
All right.
中文字幕
So that was a lot all at once.
But any questions on cookies and the feature they provide,
中文字幕
these things called sessions?
Anything at a all?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Is the session saved on the user side or the server?
中文字幕
Really good question.
And the answer can be it depends.
中文字幕
You could store on the user's client, on their browser.
And as the gentleman over here proposed, you could theoretically store literally
中文字幕
their user name and password-- maybe I proposed that earlier--
on their computer.
中文字幕
And that's bad for the reasons that we surmised earlier.
But you could also store the contents of their shopping cart, foos, bars,
中文字幕
and bazes.
That's not quite as invasive as storing their password.
中文字幕
But if you're buying things you don't really want people knowing,
that is then invasive.
中文字幕
So maybe we can do better.
And better is often, store it on the server.
中文字幕
So a well-designed website will typically
store only this big random value, the hand stamp, on the Mac or PC.
中文字幕
And then all of the interesting and maybe sensitive stuff
is stored in a database or CSV file or just the server's RAM or memory
中文字幕
like in a global variable.
Good question.
中文字幕
Other questions?
No.
中文字幕
All right.
So that's one problem solved.
中文字幕
We know now we can implement login forms.
And we know that we can remember that people are logged in.
中文字幕
So let's just stipulate that is now possible.
But over the past couple of weeks, it's not been incredibly powerful
中文字幕
to only have access to things like CSV files, comma separated values, which
create the illusion of Excel and Google Spreadsheets
中文字幕
and Apple Numbers like columns and rows.
Why?
中文字幕
Well, it's pretty much a linear search for everything, right?
A CSV file is just rows and rows and rows and rows of data.
中文字幕
And if you want to search for anything in that
file, like you might have wanted to for your survey implementation,
中文字幕
how do you find it?
Well, you open the file with Open.
中文字幕
You maybe use a for loop and iterate over every single line
looking for some value, and then you close the file.
中文字幕
That is big O of n.
And in the worst case, the thing you care about is at the very end.
中文字幕
And it's not terribly efficient.
Now, you can append to files pretty efficiently.
中文字幕
Recall that when we opened files with quote unquote, "A" for Append mode.
We did this with a brief example, instead of "W" for Write.
中文字幕
You get the operating system's help and add rose to the file
at the very bottom, which is more efficient.
中文字幕
But you can't insert things in the middle very efficiently.
You can't delete things very easily.
中文字幕
You would have to literally, for those kinds of scenarios, open the file,
read the whole darn thing, then write out parts of it
中文字幕
or add to it as you're writing out.
And so humans years ago realized, well, this is stupid.
中文字幕
All of us humans in the world are constantly
writing code to open files, change files, save files.
中文字幕
Why don't a few of us do an even better job of implementing that feature,
then share it with the world?
中文字幕
And thus were born, effectively, databases.
And these days, there are so many different types of databases--
中文字幕
you might be familiar with tools, commercial software like Oracle,
or SQL Server, or Microsoft Access.
中文字幕
And in the open source world, there's Postgres and MySQL,
and SQLite and others.
中文字幕
And many of them, as even those names imply,
use a special language called SQL, Structured Query Language, which
中文字幕
is the very last language we'll introduce
you to in CS50 unless you go off on your own with final projects
中文字幕
to pick up something more.
But with SQL, you have the ability to select data from a database,
中文字幕
to insert it, to delete it, to updated it.
All of the things that you could absolutely do with Python and CSVs,
中文字幕
it would just be so darn tedious to write those lines of code yourself.
So what's the right mental model?
中文字幕
Here is, I claim, essentially a database.
Like most everyone in this room has probably
中文字幕
used Google Spreadsheets, and if you've not, probably
Excel or maybe Apple Numbers.
中文字幕
So these are spreadsheets.
And they're essentially what you could call a relational database.
中文字幕
Relational-- implying that there's relationships
among the various data in the rows and the columns decided by you
中文字幕
or whoever made it.
And this is a spreadsheet of course.
中文字幕
And it has rows where your actual data goes.
And columns-- and what's noteworthy about the columns?
中文字幕
It's just conventional to do what with the columns,
especially in that first row?
中文字幕
Headers.
Yeah, put some header values, right?
中文字幕
You could certainly put them in the left.
It's just humans prefer, it seems, to read top
中文字幕
to bottom instead of left to all the way to the right.
So we just adopted a conventioneers ago that your columns represent
中文字幕
different types of data, and the rows represent different values
for those fields or for those columns, so to speak.
中文字幕
So if you wanted to store a spreadsheet of values
for a bunch of students in a class or in a university,
中文字幕
one column might be ID number, like their Harvard ID or the Yale ID.
Another column might be their name, their email address, phone number, age,
中文字幕
and so forth.
And you could just lay that all out.
中文字幕
You can make it pretty and boldface the top and organize things and sort it.
But at some point, this isn't quite the right tool.
中文字幕
And in fact, I ran into this in grad school years
ago where I was analyzing large sets of data.
中文字幕
And it was just convenient to double-click on the CSV file,
open it in Excel, and just manipulate it and answer the data
中文字幕
questions that I had.
But back in the day, Excel actually had a limit of 65,536 rows.
中文字幕
Sounds like a lot--
and that's 2 to the 16th power, if you call the reference there.
中文字幕
And so humans at Microsoft decided years ago, that's enough.
And frankly, it kind of was.
中文字幕
Because even in the thousands of rows, like,
my Mac just became unusable because it was just too much memory being used.
中文字幕
So it was just an impractical limit anyway.
But at some point, you might want to store
中文字幕
65,537 rows of data or hundreds of thousands of rows or millions of rows
or even more.
中文字幕
I mean, there are so many websites, Google and Facebook
and others that surely do this already.
中文字幕
You can't just use a program on your Mac or PC anymore.
You need to use fancier software.
中文字幕
But that fancier software often still works the same way.
You have one main file called a spreadsheet in our human world.
中文字幕
But in the server world, you might call it a database instead.
And whereas, in our human world, we might
中文字幕
have things called Sheets or individual spreadsheets within the bigger file,
in a database, you're going to have things called tables.
中文字幕
But they're the exact same thing with rows and columns.
And so when we want to actually store data,
中文字幕
we can actually store it in exactly those ways.
So let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up Google Spreadsheets just
as representative of a database.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and create a new file here.
So New Spreadsheet-- and just so that we can represent things like students.
中文字幕
I'm going to call this spreadsheet Students.
And over here I'm going to put their ID number and their name, and what
中文字幕
are some other fields I rattled off that come to mind?
Email.
中文字幕
Dorm.
Say again.
中文字幕
Dorm.
Good.
中文字幕
Sports and stuff they want to do.
OK.
中文字幕
So sports they want to do, sure.
That's fine-- a little longer.
中文字幕
What else?
Graduation year.
中文字幕
Graduation year, age, OK, good.
So graduation year, age, concentration--
中文字幕
OK, and we can probably keep going, and it just gets wider and wider.
And these are my columns, if you will, or the fields in the database.
中文字幕
And frankly, I could name this if I really want to be tidy here,
and I could call this Students.
中文字幕
And you know what?
Maybe I should call this not students but university.
中文字幕
Because I might want to have another tab here that we'll preemptively
name to, say, faculty.
中文字幕
And faculty probably have ID numbers, and they have names,
and they probably have departments, for instance.
中文字幕
And they also probably have emails and so forth.
So phone number is another one.
中文字幕
But I might want to kind of cluster these different types
of data in different spreadsheets because they're
中文字幕
kind of apples and oranges.
There might be some overlap, but they're distinct inside different sheets.
中文字幕
In the database world, you do the exact same thing,
except you call the whole thing a database,
中文字幕
and you call these things tables to be clear.
But more importantly, with a real database, so to speak,
中文字幕
you have to be a little more proactive about telling the database what
types of data you want to store.
中文字幕
Now, those of you who've used Google Spreadsheets and Apple
numbers and Excel know that you can go to the format menu or the data menu
中文字幕
or whatever, and you can show things to different decimal places.
You can turn things to percents.
中文字幕
And you can format the data.
But that doesn't tend to have any functional impact on your data.
中文字幕
It's just an aesthetic detail, like, how long or short do
you want to show the numbers to be in your columns and cells.
中文字幕
But with databases, you can actually provide juicy hints
to the database that will help that database store and find data for you
中文字幕
more efficiently.
For instance, there's this laundry list of data types
中文字幕
to which we have access in SQL.
So SQL is the language with which we're going to be able to query a database.
中文字幕
Frankly, in something like Google Spreadsheets and Microsoft Excel,
how do you find data?
中文字幕
We'll usually hit Command-F or Control-F, and you search for it.
That's not very programmatic.
中文字幕
You can do it with macros and such.
And we'll do this with code.
中文字幕
But with SQL, you're going to have to make a few decisions first.
SQL supports a few different data types, at least, in one of its forms.
中文字幕
So it turns out there's a lot of competition out there.
SQL is a general language.
中文字幕
But different companies and different nonprofit groups
have come up with their own dialects.
中文字幕
So much like we humans might speak--
bunches of us might speak Spanish.
中文字幕
Well, there are different variations of Spanish, not to mention
many, many, many other languages.
中文字幕
And so similarly, in the programming world,
as there's sort of a common subset of words in a language.
中文字幕
But then different companies and different people
might have added and subtracted their own features just because they think
中文字幕
that's better for their use cases.
So in SQLite, which is the database technology we will use in CS50 IDE,
中文字幕
and Android uses this, and it's very popular in other contexts
too, IOS as well--
中文字幕
they only have a few data types.
Blob, of all things, integer, numeric, real, and text.
中文字幕
Now what does that mean?
Well, it turns out, it means different things with different databases.
中文字幕
In another popular database, it's called Postgres or PostgreSQL.
This is a very popular one for high-performing websites.
中文字幕
So if you're trying to build a business, you're
trying to make an application used by everyone on campus, generally,
中文字幕
you would use a fancier technology than SQLite, which is, by definition,
lightweight.
中文字幕
And you'd do something like Postgres.
And so we'll introduce you to both of these dialects along the way
中文字幕
because each of them allows us to do different things
with a different degree of precision.
中文字幕
So in SQL, let's claim, even though it's a simplification,
there are at least these data types.
中文字幕
When deciding what type of data to store in your database table,
you have to decide, not just what it's called, like ID, and name, and email,
中文字幕
and dorm.
You have to decide what data type it is.
中文字幕
So we've kind of come full circle.
Because the last time we did this was in what language?
中文字幕
C.
So in SQL too you do this, but it's not to be nitpicky.
中文字幕
It's to actually improve performance.
So this is to help you get at that data more efficiently.
中文字幕
Because the more the server, the database, knows about your data,
the faster it can find it essentially.
中文字幕
So in the world of databases, you generally
have to decide, not just to store an integer, but either
中文字幕
a small int of integer, or a big int.
And generally speaking, at least in most databases, this might be 2 bytes.
中文字幕
This might be 4 bytes.
This might be 8 bytes.
中文字幕
So let's maybe impress the families here.
If you have a 32-bit integer, or 4 bytes,
中文字幕
what's the biggest integer you can store in your database?
(WHISPERS) 4 billion.
中文字幕
Someone please, impress.
4 billion.
中文字幕
4 billion is exactly correct.
And it might be 4 billion positive values, or maybe it's only 2 billion
中文字幕
if you also want to have 2 billion or so negative numbers as well.
Big int uses 64-bit, which is just massively, massively bigger.
中文字幕
And tiny int or small int rather--
there's also tiny int in some dialects-- small int is just 2 bytes,
中文字幕
and it actually counts up as high as 65,535, as I alluded to earlier.
So you just need to decide.
中文字幕
Now, why would you choose one or the other, when you could just use big int
and store small numbers and big numbers alike?
中文字幕
Well, why might you just intuitively not want to make all of your integer values
in a database big ints.
中文字幕
It's just simple-- give me as much headroom as I want.
You would be using memory.
中文字幕
Yeah.
You're just using memory unnecessarily, right?
中文字幕
Why use more memory than you need to?
Now, arguably-- god, memory is so cheap these days.
中文字幕
Computers are getting bigger and faster.
So in some contexts, it's not a big deal.
中文字幕
But if you have lots of data, and every one of your rows in a database
is 2 bytes bigger than needs to be, and you have 1 million rows,
中文字幕
that's already huge numbers of bytes that you're just wasting and throwing
away.
中文字幕
So it behooves you to actually give some thought to these data types.
Of course, you don't want to go too small
中文字幕
because, if you use a small int or maybe even an integer,
but business is so darn good that you have over 4 billion users or 4
中文字幕
billion rows or 4 billion foos and bars and bazes that have been sold,
which absolutely happens to the Googles and Facebooks of the world,
中文字幕
you better start using 64 bits to represent unique values instead of just
32.
中文字幕
Because eventually, you'll run out.
Well, what else?
中文字幕
Besides integer values in SQL, you might want to use floating point values.
Those are real numbers that have decimal points in them.
中文字幕
This is quite like C. They're called a little something different.
And annoyingly, it uses two words in this case.
中文字幕
But a real number is a 32-bit value that is a floating point
value, like a float in C, and double precision
中文字幕
is like a double in C, which is 64-bits.
And that just lets you get even finer-grained control
中文字幕
over the decimal point as we've seen.
Because of course, you can't represent numbers precisely
中文字幕
because of imprecision, as we've seen in both Python and C.
Numeric is kind of a catch-all for a bunch of number-related things
中文字幕
that aren't quite integers or reals necessarily.
Boolean, a true or false value, dates if you
中文字幕
want to literally store, like, year, year, year, year, dash, month, month,
dash, day, day in a standard computer format,
中文字幕
even though human cultures vary how they write that.
Datetime if you want have a date and a time right after it--
中文字幕
numeric is actually a solution to a problem.
Turns out that, finally, after all this time,
中文字幕
we have a built-in mechanism for storing numbers precisely.
And this is perfectly timed because, in CS50 Finance, when
中文字幕
you're dealing with money, it would kind of be nice if you don't accidentally
round off how much money someone has either slightly lower or slightly
中文字幕
higher.
Those of you may be families especially because, from a few movies back
中文字幕
in the day, if you ever saw Superman III,
this is how some money was made by shaving fractions of pennies
中文字幕
off of computer systems and, more moderately, Office Space.
Office Space did this as well-- big scam trying to round off these pennies.
中文字幕
Well, if you use the right technology and language, with SQL,
you can actually specify a numeric data type, which is like a floating point
中文字幕
value, but you specify, essentially, the total number of digits you
want it to handle and how many of them should be after the decimal point.
中文字幕
So it's common in stock markets to actually use
four decimal points of precision.
中文字幕
So not just cents to the tenths and the hundredths place,
but to the thousandths and ten-thousandths place,
中文字幕
you can now specify that with a value of four for precision.
And you don't have to worry about those round
中文字幕
off errors we talked about before.
Time and time stamps-- just how much time
中文字幕
has passed since the date and date and time are also available to you in SQL.
And then lastly here, text values--
中文字幕
turns out you have a choice of values for when
it comes to deciding how many characters do you use to store your data.
中文字幕
You can use char, which just like in C with an array,
you have to decide in advance for a string how many bytes to use.
中文字幕
And if you say char 8, you are getting 8 bytes.
And if the name is Malan, M-A-L-A-N, you are wasting 3,
中文字幕
or if we null terminate it, 2 of those bytes.
But SQL introduces a solution that Python kind of gave us too.
中文字幕
Varchar as the name implies-- variable number of chars
allows you to specify just an upper bound.
中文字幕
So if you know that one of your columns is going to be called Name.
And a person's name might be M-A-L-A-N-- like five letters,
中文字幕
or maybe certainly more for people with longer last names are first names,
you can say varchar 100.
中文字幕
And that's the upper bound on how long it is.
But the database will be smart.
中文字幕
If you only need five characters or 5 bytes,
it won't waste 95 others for you.
中文字幕
It will optimize that for you.
And then lastly text, if you want to store tens of thousands,
中文字幕
like paragraphs or pages of text, that's even bigger than varchar
where you don't necessarily want a well-defined upper bound.
中文字幕
You just want a good chunk of memory.
But there are implications here.
中文字幕
And just quickly, char and varchar seem not even complimentary.
Just char seems unnecessary.
中文字幕
Why paint yourself into a corner and say give me
only 8 bytes when you could just say, eh, give me
中文字幕
up to 100 bites, and you, the database server,
figure out how many to actually use?
中文字幕
Why do these two data types exist?
Yeah?
中文字幕
Time.
It would be longer to run.
中文字幕
Yeah.
So time is spot on.
中文字幕
It might actually take longer to use one data type or the other.
How could that possibly be?
中文字幕
Well, if you've got a value like char where you specify
a precise number of characters like 8.
中文字幕
If you think about the columns in Google Spreadsheets and Excel,
every one of those columns, those cells is exactly the same width, right?
中文字幕
It's 8 bytes, 8 bytes, 8 bytes, 8 bytes.
And as soon as you have perfectly constant offsets--
中文字幕
this is byte 0, this is 8, this is 16, this is 24, this is 32,
and so forth, you reintroduce the capability
中文字幕
that in C we had with arrays.
You have random access doing simple, simple arithmetic-- multiplication,
中文字幕
addition, and subtraction, you can just jump to any element in a column
if it's using the same number of bytes for every cell.
中文字幕
But with varchar, if you need to have small narrow cells and wide cells,
you're going to have what's called a ragged array where
中文字幕
one side of it, the left-hand side, so to speak,
is going to be very straight and rigid.
中文字幕
But the other side my kind of vary based on how long the word is in that column.
And to your point about time, it's going to take the computer more time
中文字幕
to search a varchar field.
Because it can't just jump to the third element.
中文字幕
It has to search all of them, potentially.
But thankfully, at the end of the day, databases don't do that.
中文字幕
They don't just devolve into linear search.
CSVs devolve, for our purposes, into linear search.
中文字幕
The magic and the intellectual property and the secret sauce, so to speak,
that goes into databases--
中文字幕
Oracle SQL Server, Microsoft Access, Postgres, MySQL, and SQLite
is that really smart computer scientists have decided to implement algorithms
中文字幕
and fancy data structures, often tree-based--
if you recall our discussion of binary trees
中文字幕
or tries on a hash tables and those fancier data structures-- they
had baked those kinds of data structures and designs
中文字幕
into their database software.
They've made it freely available or commercially available.
中文字幕
And so we now just have an abstraction called a database
into which we can store data and just read it, update it, write it,
中文字幕
and change it quickly without having to implement all
of that low-level plumbing ourselves.
中文字幕
And so that's ultimately what a database is going to give us.
But we have to actually have access to a database to do that.
中文字幕
And we need to actually decide first to help
the database by telling it what to store where and how to store it as a type.
中文字幕
So why don't we do this?
Let me go ahead and do exactly that with a couple of examples.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up CS50 IDE again,
our web-based programming environment.
中文字幕
And let me go into our Terminal window.
So for those unfamiliar, a terminal window is just this black and white
中文字幕
or this blue and white window in which you can type commands.
And rather than point and click and double click on things,
中文字幕
you can only do things textually in this window.
And it turns out that, in the world of SQLite,
中文字幕
we can actually use a command called SQLite3,
which allows us to create a database.
中文字幕
So in our human world, for CSVs, you've seen how, in code, you
can just create rows and columns.
中文字幕
You can literally type it in a text box.
SQLite is a database technology that uses binary format, 0s and 1s.
中文字幕
And so you're going to have to actually store your data differently
using a program.
中文字幕
So if I want to make a file called, for instance, froshims.db,
I can literally say SQLite three froshims.db,
中文字幕
and then I'm in this program.
This is a text-based program via which I can create my rows and columns.
中文字幕
And it, by designer, is going to be a little arcane for a moment.
It's going to look a little cryptic.
中文字幕
But if I want to go ahead and create a table, like a spreadsheet in here,
I'm going to literally type CREATE TABLE.
中文字幕
I'm going to call this registrants just like last week
when we were looking at froshims examples.
中文字幕
And the freshman intramural sports program
has students registering for sports.
中文字幕
So I'm going to have a registrants table here.
I'm going to go ahead now and specify that I
中文字幕
want a few columns for this database table, one of which I want to call ID,
one of which I want to call name, and one of which I want to call dorm.
中文字幕
So I'm going to keep-- whoops.
I didn't mean to hit Enter.
中文字幕
Let me just clean this up.
So now I have three columns, ID, name, and dorm.
中文字幕
And if I were to hit Enter, theoretically, it
should create a database.
中文字幕
It's not going to be graphical like Excel or Google Spreadsheets,
but it will exist in my IDE in a file called froshims.db.
中文字幕
But I can't just hit Enter yet.
Because I have to tell the database a bit more.
中文字幕
I need to tell it that, you know what?
My ID value should probably be an integer.
中文字幕
And you know what?
My name should probably be char, or varchar?
中文字幕
What should the name of a student be stored as?
varchar.
中文字幕
Varchar, OK?
So varchar because they're going to vary, right?
中文字幕
If you can think of bunches of your friends,
they might have short names or long names.
中文字幕
OK, what's the upper bound?
What's the length of your friends' longest name?
中文字幕
50.
16?
中文字幕
All right.
Is anyone in here having a name, first name and last, that's longer than 16?
中文字幕
That's 50, sorry.
Oh, 50.
中文字幕
Sorry.
I heard 16, I thought.
中文字幕
Because you're not going be able to register for froshims
because the database is going to truncate.
中文字幕
And as an aside, if you've ever gone to a website and tried typing into a form
field and either your keyboard stops working
中文字幕
or you do type a long word or paragraph in, and then you hit Enter,
and it's some of it's gone, well, that's because the database likely
中文字幕
can only store so many bytes.
And frankly, this often happens on customer service forums, right?
中文字幕
They don't really want you being too verbose with the customer support
staff.
中文字幕
They'll cap the length of the field into which you're typing.
And they're also doing that on the database,
中文字幕
but also probably for practical human reasons,
they don't want to read a big complaint that's this long as well.
中文字幕
So 50-- anyone have a name longer than 50 characters?
Yeah, not many names.
中文字幕
But you know what?
We have technology to answer this.
中文字幕
Longest name in world--
and it's this guy.
中文字幕
Guinness Book of World Records is probably right.
So his name is Barnaby Marmaduke Aloysius Benjy Cobweb Dartagnan Egbert
中文字幕
Felix Gaspar Humbert Ignatius Jayden Kasper Leroy Maximilian Neddy Obiajulu
Pepin Quilliam Rosenkranz Sexton Teddy Upwood Vivatma Wayland Xylon Yardley
中文字幕
Zachary Usansky.
But he also goes by Nick, apparently.
中文字幕
But OK.
Let me go ahead and highlight this.
中文字幕
And I could count this manually.
But I'm sure someone has made a website to count characters in a string.
中文字幕
There we go, lettercount.com.
OK.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and paste that in, count the characters, 225--
so nick will not be registering unless we don't support just 16 or 50.
中文字幕
Looks like we need at least 225.
So at some point, you do have to make a decision.
中文字幕
And honestly, it's not always obvious.
You do have to specify that varchar is going to be-- eh, it could be 16,
中文字幕
could be 50, could be 225.
But you know what? if he has kids--
中文字幕
so let's just round up a bit and call it varchar 255, honestly,
only because it was a convention.
中文字幕
So back in the day, 255 tended to be the max length
for this field in older databases.
中文字幕
And that at least feels like it's probably enough wiggle room for names.
But you have to make a judgment call at some point.
中文字幕
We could ignore the problem say 1,000 characters.
But if that's never really going to happen,
中文字幕
and your potentially wasting space, you probably shouldn't.
Because even though it's an upper bound, you're sacrificing something like time,
中文字幕
potentially, to search that field if you're just
telling the database that it's going to be bigger than it ever actually
中文字幕
will be.
It needs to be more finely hinted.
中文字幕
So what about dorm?
Oh, god, now we have to do this again.
中文字幕
How do we do it with dorm?
What's the longest length of a dorm or a house on campus?
中文字幕
I'm, like, OK ,, house maybe.
But honestly, at some point, it doesn't matter too much.
中文字幕
But being consistent is what matters.
It's a matter of style.
中文字幕
It's a matter of design.
At some point, you don't have to nitpick every little value.
中文字幕
But you should probably pick some reasonable value
that you could justify to a roommate or to a colleague or to a teaching fellow.
中文字幕
And then say this feels like enough without it being actually excessive.
And there's one last thing I'm going to do here is just
中文字幕
end my thought with a semicolon.
I apologize, they're back.
中文字幕
But at the end of my start here, if I haven't made any typographical errors,
and I'm going to go and hit Enter.
中文字幕
Nothing seems to happen.
And ironically, in CS50, in programming, nothing happening
中文字幕
is usually a good thing because it means no errors have happened.
If, in SQLite, I type schema, I can actually
中文字幕
just see a regurgitation of the table I just created.
But more importantly, I can start to insert data into this.
中文字幕
Now unfortunately, it's not yet graphical.
But if I want to insert data into this, I can do this.
中文字幕
INSERT INTO registrants-- well, what do you want to insert?
I want to go ahead and insert an ID, a name, and a dorm.
中文字幕
Well, with what values?
Well, with these values--
中文字幕
the ID will be-- the first registrant will be 1.
The first one to register will be Brian.
中文字幕
And his dorm, Brian where did you live?
BRIAN: Out on Pennypacker.
中文字幕
Pennypacker.
So it's good.
中文字幕
That might be close to four timer too lengthwise.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Here is an example of a SQL statement.
CREATE TABLE is one verb or expression you can use.
中文字幕
INSERT INTO is another.
You specify the name of the table, the fields of the table, and then values.
中文字幕
And now I'm capitalizing just to make clear what are SQL commands
and what are actually just words I, the human developer, chose.
中文字幕
But it's just a convention.
These uppercase words could probably be lower case in most contexts too.
中文字幕
But it helps things, I think visually, to distinguish.
Now I go ahead and enter.
中文字幕
Nothing seemed to happen.
That's probably a good thing.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and register one other person.
I'll be the second registrant.
中文字幕
So maybe David from Matthews.
And so Matthews here, Enter.
中文字幕
And now, if I want to select all of the students in the database,
I can go ahead and say SELECT FROM--
中文字幕
or you know what?
Let's select everything as denoted in many languages by star,
中文字幕
from registrants semicolon enter, and there we have it.
It's kind of a tiny super simple, lightweight database.
中文字幕
But there are my rows and columns much like Excel
and Google Spreadsheets would lay them out for me.
中文字幕
But it gets better than this.
Suppose I want to search this database for all of the students who
中文字幕
registered for Matthews.
And suppose that time passes and more students
中文字幕
actually register for forshims.
I can actually filter this data.
中文字幕
I can do something like SELECT star FROM registrants WHERE
dorm equals quote unquote, "Matthews."
中文字幕
And so I can filter it, hit Enter, and now I get back just one row.
And if your should mind starts to wander--
中文字幕
wow, if I could introduce Python or JavaScript into this,
you know what I could do?
中文字幕
I could probably get back, not this and this ASCII-based table, this text
table.
中文字幕
Maybe I could get back an actual list of rows
so that I can actually do something with that data.
中文字幕
And that's, indeed, where we're going with this.
So if I want to select someone else, I could do hmm--
中文字幕
maybe SELECT just the NAME from registrants
where dorm equals "Mathews."
中文字幕
If I only care about knowing who registered,
I could do that and whittle it down to even less data.
中文字幕
So already, in just these few commands, I
can express so much more functionality than you could with a CSV.
中文字幕
To do this and CSV, you would have had to write all
of these lines of Python code yourself.
中文字幕
What if Brian moved?
So Brian really didn't like the Union dorm,
中文字幕
so we're going to go ahead and UPDATE registrants
and SET dorm equal to-- where do want to move to?
中文字幕
BRIAN: Canaday.
"Canaday" WHERE--
中文字幕
I could do this a few ways.
What's your instinct?
中文字幕
How could I identify Brian and only Brian so--
I don't want to move to Canaday.
中文字幕
How do we move just Brian?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Maybe we could WHERE name equals quote unquote "Brian" and Enter.
I like this, but someone find fault with this if you could.
中文字幕
Two Brians.
If there are two Brians, we're moving both of them
中文字幕
are all three of them.
So maybe better, honestly, would be to say, mm,
中文字幕
let's just say where the ID equals 1.
Now, of course, I need to know Brian's Harvard ID number or whatnot.
中文字幕
But this is going to be more precise.
Because the supposition here is that the leftmost column or ID
中文字幕
field, by human convention, should be unique so that it uniquely identifies
the room so we can have as many Brians as we want,
中文字幕
but we're not going to confuse them.
If I go ahead and hit Enter now, nothing seems to happen.
中文字幕
But if I select star from registrants again, and hit Enter, notice now,
Brian has indeed been moved to Canaday.
中文字幕
So there are so many other things.
Brian, you know what?
中文字幕
You're not very good at sports the team concluded.
So delete from registrants WHERE ID equals 1.
中文字幕
And now if we select star from registrants, we have just me left.
But Brian is gone as well.
中文字幕
So we have the ability to INSERT, to SELECT, to UPDATE, and DELETE,
and CREATE, all the while filtering.
中文字幕
And we've only just scratched the surface here of what's possible.
Because it turns out, we can store so much data in these databases.
中文字幕
All of our students, all of our faculty--
if you're a company, you can start to store
中文字幕
all of the products in your database, all of the orders,
all of your customers.
中文字幕
But as soon as you start going down that road, well, gee, what's a customer?
Customers have names and ID numbers and maybe email addresses
中文字幕
and postal addresses.
Those are going to get messy-- phone numbers,
中文字幕
which are kind of like integers, but not quite.
So there are so many questions we still need to answer.
中文字幕
But feels like it's time for some fruit and some muffins.
So why don't we go ahead and take a five-minute break, turn on some music.
中文字幕
If parents need to depart, that's fine.
And we'll see you back here in five or so minutes.
中文字幕
All right.
So we're back.
中文字幕
And where we left off was exactly here using
SQLite3, which is the version 3 of the SQLite command, which
中文字幕
is just a text-based interface to the technology
that we should think of as SQLite.
中文字幕
SQLite is interesting and it's lightweight in the sense
that it's not a server, it's not fancy software that you have to run.
中文字幕
It literally stores all of your data in a file, but that, by convention,
ends in .db or maybe even .sqlite.
中文字幕
But it's just a binary file, 0s and 1s.
It's not text that you can open with Excel or something like that.
中文字幕
So it's not a CSV.
So it's stored on file.
中文字幕
This means that you don't need particular experience
with setting up a database server.
中文字幕
You don't need memory and software to actually run on the computer.
You can store everything locally, but you do pay a price.
中文字幕
Because recall from our past discussions, disks are slow.
And if you're storing your data on the disk,
中文字幕
it's not going to be nearly as fast as storing it only in RAM.
And that's why these other technologies like Postgres and MySQL,
中文字幕
and Microsoft Access, and SQL Server, and Oracle exist.
Those are fancier products where someone literally does double-click an icon
中文字幕
or run a command that runs a program that
stays running in the computer's memory and gives you even better performance.
中文字幕
But for our purposes, pedagogically SQLite is handy.
But we're still going to ask the questions about data types
中文字幕
because SQLite does support fancier data types like those in Postgres
and SQL Server, MySQL, and Oracle, and those are the lower-case ones
中文字幕
we introduced a bit ago.
But honestly, this is going to get tedious quickly.
中文字幕
Even I rarely remember exactly the right syntax when creating tables,
the order in which everything has to go.
中文字幕
So I tend to use a Graphical User Interface, or GUI myself.
And there are lots of tools out there.
中文字幕
But we've built one that's free and open source the CS50
IDE that just makes it a little easier to edit your SQL tables.
中文字幕
So I'm going to go ahead and Exit out of SQLite.
And I'm going to go ahead over here.
中文字幕
And you'll notice that we have all of the files
from today including, most recently, froshims.db.
中文字幕
That is the file I created with SQLite3.
But if you double-click it when using CS50 IDE,
中文字幕
it's actually going to open a program that's called phpLiteAdmin.
It happens to be written in another language called PHP,
中文字幕
has nothing to do with databases, just the name of the product here.
But it's a tool that, using pretty simple HTML tables,
中文字幕
just gives us a graphical user interface over the exact same functionality.
And personally, I just find this easier to use.
中文字幕
And pedagogically, it's going to be better
because it's going to show us the available data types for our table.
中文字幕
So for instance, notice here-- there's a lot going on the screen.
But a lot of this is just uninteresting details.
中文字幕
But notice here, I see a table called registrants.
And then I can browse it.
中文字幕
I can see its structure.
I can execute manual SQL by typing it in.
中文字幕
I can search it, insert.
I can do bunches of things to it.
中文字幕
And that's why this graphical user interface is just convenient.
Let me go ahead and click on registrants.
中文字幕
And by default, you'll see these tabs now, Browse, Structure, SQL, and then
a bunch of others.
中文字幕
And notice over here.
You'll see the one row and the one registrant who actually remains.
中文字幕
Because when we last left off, we removed Brian forcibly from the team.
So suppose I want to go ahead and add more rows just
中文字幕
for the sake of discussion.
I can just do it manually here.
中文字幕
I can go in here and I can say, let's say the third player
is going to be Veronica.
中文字幕
I think she was also in Matthews so I can just type that in here.
And I can just go ahead and click Insert.
中文字幕
But what's nice about phpLiteAdmin is that it will not only
insert the rows for you, it will show you
中文字幕
the SQLite code with which you could have done it yourself.
So it's a nice visual reinforcement of that exact same command.
中文字幕
And you'll notice they use double quotes instead of my single quotes before.
They're sometimes interchangeable, but not always.
中文字幕
So it's a wonderful way of just learning how you can actually
do this with the right SQL code so you're not oversimplifying it
中文字幕
with the GUI.
But you know what?
中文字幕
Let's do this.
I'm going to go ahead and start over because I
中文字幕
want to make some better decisions.
I'm going to go ahead and, literally, right-click or Control-click
中文字幕
this, delete froshims.db.
And let's actually start this from scratch.
中文字幕
Now previously when I did this, I could have,
in my Terminal window, gone ahead and done SQLite3 and then, what was it?
中文字幕
Froshims.db and created the file.
For now, I'm going to actually just go ahead and touch
中文字幕
a file called that name, which is a simple command that
just literally creates it, but puts nothing in it,
中文字幕
just so I have an empty file.
And you'll see that it just popped up again
中文字幕
on the left-hand side, which is handy.
And now I can double-click this version of it, which has nothing in it yet.
中文字幕
And I'm back to phpLiteAdmin.
But notice no table in database.
中文字幕
So let's start to ask some of the harder questions
as to actually how to create data in a database.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and go to this field here-- create
new table on database froshims.
中文字幕
I'll go ahead and call it registrants again.
But how many fields?
中文字幕
So let's go with ID, name, and dorm, what else?
Email I heard earlier.
中文字幕
Age I heard earlier.
Sports you want to be in.
中文字幕
Sorry.
So sports you want-- excuse me--
中文字幕
sports you want to be in.
OK. six fields, six fields, let's go with that.
中文字幕
So it's, actually, you know what?
Seven fields.
中文字幕
I want phone numbers too this time.
So let me go ahead and click Go.
中文字幕
And now you'll see just a GUI way of prompting you for all the answers
to the same questions as before.
中文字幕
And maybe this is clearer.
Maybe it's not.
中文字幕
But just no alternative to the memorizing
exactly what the commands need to be.
中文字幕
So top to bottom, here are all of the fields I need to decide on.
Ironically, the fields is just a synonym for columns.
中文字幕
And yet my columns are currently laid out in rows,
but that's just a UI issue.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and decide.
By convention, my first field is almost always ID or probably should be.
中文字幕
And we'll see why this is powerful and just a little bit.
The data type for that, by convention, should be integer,
中文字幕
unless you've got a lot of data like a Facebook,
and then big int might make more sense.
中文字幕
But notice this Dropdown actually gives us
a nice menu of options just as before.
中文字幕
And you'll see in gray text, the category,
or in fancy terms, the affinity of these various types in SQLite
中文字幕
and in lower case black words here, you'll
see the actual data type supported by big popular databases like Postgres
中文字幕
that you might want to use for your final projects.
In fact, we're introducing these with eye
中文字幕
toward your using these for final projects in the cloud, not in CS50 IDE,
but actually getting your own domain name
中文字幕
and putting your website, if you do a web app, out there.
So here, we have all of my available types.
中文字幕
And under Integer, I'm going to go ahead and literally choose Integer for my ID.
All right.
中文字幕
Next, go ahead and Zoom Out.
Let me go ahead and choose a student's name.
中文字幕
Before did we do did we decide on char or varchar?
varchar.
中文字幕
OK, varchar, and what size?
255.
中文字幕
So the user interface here just allows me to type it in.
So the syntax is a little different because it's a GUI, but 255.
中文字幕
But you know what?
The last field was dorm.
中文字幕
That too, I think we said varchar.
So let me choose that.
中文字幕
And 255, though, this one's a little more debatable.
I'm not sure what the right number is, so in the absence of clarity,
中文字幕
I'm just going to standardize on some same value without being too wasteful.
But notice there are a few questions here that we haven't come to.
中文字幕
But our perfect segue earlier hinted at this.
It turns out, you need to make a few other decisions
中文字幕
when designing a database.
If you know in advance that one of your fields
中文字幕
is the primary piece of data to uniquely identify users,
that's what's going to be called a primary key--
中文字幕
the column or fields that, guaranteed, is going to identify users uniquely.
So if you've got two Brians, each of them is going to have its own ID.
中文字幕
That therefore, is your primary key, not the name field Brian.
So I'm going to tell the database, this is the primary key.
中文字幕
And it's going to help me keep track of that uniqueness.
Moreover, this is a fancy feature.
中文字幕
Before, I was manually and very arbitrarily
saying Brian will be number 1, I'll be number 2, Veronica will be number 3.
中文字幕
That's tedious.
Like, computer should be able to solve that problem for me.
中文字幕
I don't want to think about who is idea number what.
You can auto-increment the field.
中文字幕
So if I actually check this box, SQL for me
will just plus-plus, plus-plus the idea field every time
中文字幕
I insert a new name and a new dorm.
I don't have to even bother specifying an ID anymore.
中文字幕
Now there's another column here, not null,
where you can specify this column should never be null.
中文字幕
And this is important because, if you're building a website that has important
data that you must have from the users-- like,
中文字幕
your app won't work without the user's username or their password
or their email address--
中文字幕
you can say not null.
And your database will ensure that you can't even
中文字幕
insert a row into this database unless you give it a value for that field.
So it helps you protect you against yourself.
中文字幕
Because you could certainly implement that
logically in Python or any language.
中文字幕
But the database is a final gauntlet as well.
A default value doesn't really make sense here.
中文字幕
But for certain types of fields, you can say, database,
insert the current time or the current date for me?
中文字幕
Now, why might you want that?
Why date and time by default?
中文字幕
Why might that be useful?
When the account was created?
中文字幕
When the account was created, when they bought
a foo, when they shipped a bar-- any number of reasons.
中文字幕
You might just want to know, what is the time right now?
But you don't have to write code for that.
中文字幕
The database can answer those questions for you.
So just so much more functionality than we got, of course, with CSVs alone.
中文字幕
So name, should it be a primary key?
No.
中文字幕
Otherwise, we couldn't have two Brians.
And generally, your primary key will be one field, though,
中文字幕
theoretically you could make joint columns if you wanted.
But generally, it'll be a single one.
中文字幕
Should we auto-increment Brian-- so it's, like, well--
Brian28, or Brian2, Brian3, and so forth?
中文字幕
No.
Doesn't really make sense.
中文字幕
Not null?
Probably.
中文字幕
I want all of the freshmen's names so that we
know who is signing up for sports.
中文字幕
And dorm?
Yeah, not null.
中文字幕
But oh, corner case--
can anyone think of a corner case where dorm maybe
中文字幕
should kind of sort of be null?
They're off-campus.
中文字幕
They commute, they're off-campus--
it's not many students.
中文字幕
But if you have 1%, 5% of students living off-campus,
this is a design question now.
中文字幕
And all of us have probably visited some website
where you just can't fill out the form in the right way
中文字幕
because you don't fit their mold or their expectations.
And that's just because of a poor design decision.
中文字幕
So let's allow it to be null just in case.
Now what else?
中文字幕
We said a phone number was when I proposed.
Gosh, there's no phone number type.
中文字幕
So what do you want to go with?
I'm sorry?
中文字幕
varchar.
Varchar.
中文字幕
OK.
So we can pick varchar and maybe use 10 or so for 10 digits in the US,
中文字幕
at least, though, maybe, like, 12 with the dashes, or 13 with the parentheses,
or--
中文字幕
What's that?
I hear murmuring.
中文字幕
Sorry.
A small int.
中文字幕
A small int and just treated
as a number, maybe that could work too.
中文字幕
Another alternative?
Anything else?
中文字幕
precision.
Precision-- so a specific number.
中文字幕
make sure you have the correct number.
Good.
中文字幕
So not a bad instinct.
But it turns out with the numeric data type, where you specify scale
中文字幕
as it's called-- the total number of digits in precision--
that's generally meant for floating point values-- so
中文字幕
real numbers with decimal points.
Because even though you're specifying a max limit,
中文字幕
you don't require that many digits.
It's just a max.
中文字幕
Yeah?
I would think that giving it--
中文字幕
doing some sort of chars would be a bad design because then you
can enter nonnumerical values.
中文字幕
Yeah.
We can kind of find fault, I think, both of these ideas, though both of them
中文字幕
are reasonable.
If you allow for char or varchar, I could
中文字幕
type in like foo or bar or baz and not a number.
So maybe we should go with int.
中文字幕
But can someone think of a counter-example to why
you shouldn't use integer?
中文字幕
It's got a variable length to it, doesn't it?
So you'd get whatever number--
中文字幕
Variable length.
But if we actually do the math, maybe 65,
中文字幕
maybe-- there are enough bytes there.
We could use a big int, and that gives us a really long phone number.
中文字幕
So there's probably a reasonable max.
Yeah?
中文字幕
Let's say  in between  integer.
Hyphens and parentheses.
中文字幕
We have to decide, do we want to support those?
And honestly, all of us are perhaps a little US-centric right now, most of us
中文字幕
here.
But when you make a local call in some zones, like, you type 0 first.
中文字幕
And some human might type 0 as their number.
But what's going to happen if you type 0 into an integer field?
中文字幕
You're going to ignore it.
So now there's that corner case.
中文字幕
So dammit.
Like, there's no way to solve this problem it would seem.
中文字幕
So what's best?
We have to make a compromise and just accept
中文字幕
that we have to solve this with code.
Varchar.
中文字幕
Varchar?
All right.
中文字幕
So varchars or char.
All right.
中文字幕
So maybe let's simplify the problem.
No one from outside the US can take freshman intramural sports.
中文字幕
That simplifies the world.
Because if we only support US phone numbers, now we can say 10 digits.
中文字幕
And if we say, you know what?
I don't care about the hyphens or the parentheses.
中文字幕
I can use code, JavaScript or Python, to throw away the syntax.
And I can just store 10 digits.
中文字幕
Maybe char 10 is sufficient--
3 for the area code, then the rest of the number, the all seven digits
中文字幕
thereof.
But you could find fault with this too.
中文字幕
And we're really alienating that international population on campus.
But again, these are just non-obvious design decisions.
中文字幕
And so here we are, at the end of the semester.
We don't always have good answers.
中文字幕
And reasonable people will disagree.
But let me simplify our assumptions and just do US numbers, 10 digits,
中文字幕
and trust that I will use code in Python or some other language
to throw away the syntax, the punctuation and whatnot
中文字幕
of parentheses and hyphens.
And I'll make sure the human hasn't typed in any letters of the alphabet.
中文字幕
I can do that in code.
And you know we can do that even in JavaScript when a human submits a form.
中文字幕
We'll leave for the end, sports, what was it sports--
Sports they want to do.
中文字幕
Sports they might want to do.
So this is a good example of, you shouldn't really have spaces
中文字幕
in your field name, so the convention would be sports_they_ really or might
or let's just call it sports in this case.
中文字幕
We'll come back to that.
I think there were two other ideas we had.
中文字幕
Phone number.
Email.
中文字幕
OK.
Email is a good one.
中文字幕
What should that one be?
There's no email type, unfortunately, even though there
中文字幕
is an HTML, an input type for email.
Varchar.
中文字幕
What's that?
Varchar.
中文字幕
Yeah, I feel like we probably need a varchar here.
But here, a little non-obvious, what is the longest email address in the world?
中文字幕
Maybe it's Nick's?
So I don't know.
中文字幕
But let's pick a reasonable upper bound that we can maybe
be comfortable with as a group.
中文字幕
And let's see-- anything else here?
No?
中文字幕
OK.
And was there one more field?
中文字幕
Graduation year.
Oh, grad-- oh, age.
中文字幕
Let's go with age.
So age-- finally, something simple.
中文字幕
What you want this to be?
Small int.
中文字幕
Small int, right.
We will not support people older than 65,535 years old.
中文字幕
Someone want to find fault with this idea though?
I would argue, there's no one right answer to any of these.
中文字幕
You need month.
Month--
中文字幕
oh, it depends.
Do we want month?
中文字幕
Yeah.
We might need .
中文字幕
--then you need the date, the year.
So you're assuming we want birth date.
中文字幕
I think I've called it age.
So maybe that's the problem.
中文字幕
Like, if it's age, small int's fine.
Like, you can be 0 years old or 65,000 years old.
中文字幕
We have a good range.
All about the age, date of birth.
中文字幕
If it's age, I think we're OK.
But I think you allude to a good point, which is, why would we maybe want
中文字幕
to store birth date and not age?
Yeah.
中文字幕
The damn thing's always changing, otherwise, right?
Like, I'm going to have to update my database tomorrow and then
中文字幕
the next day, let alone every hour or every minute just
because my users' ages are changing.
中文字幕
Like, that seems silly.
Let me, instead, fix a value--
中文字幕
so do something like birth date.
Birth date-- maybe specify not an int.
中文字幕
But let's actually use the date field.
We could store time if we really care what time they
中文字幕
were born on a certain day.
But here, I can say date is going to be a little better because, now I
中文字幕
know in Python, JavaScript, even C, I can do a little bit of math.
And if I know they were born on such and such a day and month and year,
中文字幕
well, I'll just subtract that from the current day, month, and year
and figure out how many days or years old they are-- so a better design
中文字幕
decision there perhaps.
But we do have to standardize the format.
中文字幕
We can't just allow people from the US and Europe and Asia
to all kind of choose their own formats.
中文字幕
SQL standardizes this-- year, year, year, year dash
month, month dash day, day.
中文字幕
And that's the value of having these data types again.
All right.
中文字幕
So how about sports-- the last one?
Varchar.
中文字幕
Varchar, all right.
What's the longest number of words in the sport?
中文字幕
I didn't say might want to do, so I could get up there,
but 255 probably makes the most sense.
中文字幕
Maybe unless they're very athletic.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Here too I don't know.
But just for the sake of opening up possibilities,
中文字幕
when you think the human might be a little expository
and actually write a paragraph of all the sports they're
中文字幕
involved in or whatnot or even bigger than a paragraph, text is even bigger.
Sports, this probably isn't compelling.
中文字幕
And I'll change it back to varchar.
But if someone is typing in their college essay
中文字幕
into the Common Application, or if you're
asking people to paste their resumes, or the like, you might want to use text.
中文字幕
Because I have no idea how many words someone's going to have.
Text allows you to store even more data.
中文字幕
But it stores it a little differently.
It tends to store it not in the column, but using pointers.
中文字幕
If you recall from a few weeks back, it uses the equivalent
of that to store it over there, which takes a little more time to get to.
中文字幕
So again, there's just a trade-off here.
So we could do varchar 255--
中文字幕
makes me a little nervous.
So I'm going to go with another common value.
中文字幕
1024, it's a power of 2, but there's no one right answer here.
But these are the non-obvious design decisions we have to make.
中文字幕
If I didn't make any mistakes here, I'm going
to go ahead and click Create, and whoo--
中文字幕
table has been created.
You can even see now all of the data that's been created there.
中文字幕
And voila, if I go back to froshims, and I go back to the registrants table,
not only can I browse it-- there's nothing in there yet.
中文字幕
I can look at the structure and actually see all of those same values
and edit some of them like renaming.
中文字幕
But you can't completely mutilate it.
You might have to start over if you make too many changes.
中文字幕
All right.
Any questions then about this?
中文字幕
Yeah?
Why do you use 1024 instead of 1023?
中文字幕
Oh, why do I use 1024 instead of 1023.
Typically, when you choose a ma-- oh, convention.
中文字幕
I can't justify this.
255 was the max because I think one of the bites was reserved for some value,
中文字幕
historically.
But that's not really the case.
中文字幕
That bound has been lifted, and no good reason.
You could have used 255.
中文字幕
Nowadays, yes.
Years ago, 255 was an actual limit.
中文字幕
And so it got adopted.
Now, I don't know.
中文字幕
I just pick powers of 2 often.
And then at my next go-to would be 2048, 4096, and so forth, just because.
中文字幕
Yeah?
What's the difference between varchar and char?
中文字幕
Varchar--
What's the difference between varchar and char?
中文字幕
Char uses a fixed number of bytes no matter how many of them you are using,
the advantage of which is your columns, conceptually,
中文字幕
are perfectly straight on both the left edge and the right edge, which
means you have random access because every cell is some fixed
中文字幕
number of bytes from the rest.
Varchar user a ragged array, as it's called,
中文字幕
where one side, the right-hand side is shorter or longer in different cells.
So there's only a maximum length on each of those cells.
中文字幕
But searching it can be slower as a result
because you can't just jump to cell to cell.
中文字幕
You have to follow the lengths of those things.
That's the trade-off.
中文字幕
Yeah?
If you  education, how do you add it?
中文字幕
Oh, if I wanted to add an education field now and modify
the table--
中文字幕
if you realize too late, oh, darn, like, I need to actually add something
to this, in the GUI tool, we can add 1 fields to the end of the table,
中文字幕
literally.
So let's do that.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and click Go.
I'll be prompted with a similar form, but smaller.
中文字幕
I can go ahead and type in something like education.
Let me propose this is varchar, maybe 255,
中文字幕
though we could have that debate too.
I'm going to go ahead and say add fields.
中文字幕
And now notice that the table has been altered successfully.
It actually, for whatever reason, it's not showing me
中文字幕
the code for that particular command.
But there is literally an ALTER command in SQL
中文字幕
that would allow you to change it.
And if I go back to the structure now, you'll
中文字幕
see that I have another column called education shown ironically
here as a row.
中文字幕
Yeah?
Does the order of the columns matter?
中文字幕
Good question.
Does the order of the columns matter?
中文字幕
Fundamentally, no.
By convention, you would typically put the ID first.
中文字幕
And then I, personally, by design, put the most important fields
next like name feels like the right choice,
中文字幕
maybe email feels like the right choice, though, I clearly thought
of it a little too late this time.
中文字幕
It's not easy in SQLite to reorder things, but in other databases you can.
So there, it's more of a human convention.
中文字幕
Yeah?
Is it convention to have one single primary key,
中文字幕
or can you have multiple?
Good question.
中文字幕
Is it a convention to have one single primary key, or can you have multiple?
By definition, you can only have one.
中文字幕
But that primary key can span multiple columns.
So we haven't seen a use case for this yet.
中文字幕
But there are scenarios in which you would want to say,
I want to guarantee that these two columns together are unique,
中文字幕
but not each individual one unique.
But we won't encounter that just yet.
中文字幕
Other questions, yeah?
What if you had added education
中文字幕
after you had started the database, and that was a not null field?
Really good question.
中文字幕
What if you had added education after you already had real data in there,
but you specified not null, which is problematic.
中文字幕
Because what is the educational backgrounds of the previous people?
Typically, what the database would do is either reject it,
中文字幕
or it would just put the "empty string," quote unquote.
So it's not technically null, but there's nothing actually there.
中文字幕
It's just a string of length 0.
Really good question.
中文字幕
All right.
So what can we now do that's a little more powerful about this?
中文字幕
Well, let me go ahead and quickly insert some data here.
I'm going to keep most of it blank.
中文字幕
But you know what?
I'm not even going to bother with ID.
中文字幕
Brian you're back on the team.
Let's go ahead and insert Brian.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead now into registrants again.
Let's go ahead and add Veronica again.
中文字幕
So I'm just inserting a few rows manually.
And again, notice it's executing all of this for me
中文字幕
without me having to bother typing it out.
But I absolutely could.
中文字幕
In fact, just for good measure, let's do one manually.
If I click the SQL tab, notice that I get a default suggestion here.
中文字幕
That is the syntax with which you can select everything.
Or I can just type INSERT into registrants.
中文字幕
But now, if I only want to insert a name,
I don't have to do all of the columns.
中文字幕
I can just say go ahead and insert here, Erin, for instance,
semicolon, zoom out and click Go.
中文字幕
That seemed to work.
If I go back to browse now, Erin is in there as well.
中文字幕
But you'll see the difference.
The query that's being generated automatically by the GUI
中文字幕
was lazily just inserting quote unquote, the so-called empty string of length 0.
I, by omitting even mention of those columns,
中文字幕
was deliberately inserting null.
So frankly, my database is getting a little messy here.
中文字幕
So you generally don't use phpLiteAdmin or a GUI to insert data.
You might use it to conveniently create your tables
中文字幕
and get your application ready.
But then you're going to write code ultimately.
中文字幕
And that's the direction we're going.
And I'm going to go ahead and insert one more person.
中文字幕
Oh, I forgot I'm not on the team at all because we started over.
So let me put myself back on the team, David.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and click INSERT, go back to registrants,
and now you'll see there are four of us.
中文字幕
My ID changed because they've been inserted in different orders.
But notice all of the auto incrementing has been happening magically for me.
中文字幕
And that's useful because I don't have to even think about it.
And who cares what my ID is.
中文字幕
I just need to have, in many cases, in a database, a unique ID.
So now let's actually write a little bit of code, right?
中文字幕
Thus far we haven't done anything useful.
We've shown you this black and white window in which you
中文字幕
can select in certain update data.
But that doesn't really solve any problems we know about yet.
中文字幕
We have this graphical web-based interface
via which you can create tables and add data, but who cares?
中文字幕
We're trying to solve actual problems.
And the problems of late have been to build
中文字幕
software that would solve any number of human problems
like serving users and showing the results
中文字幕
or finding similarities in documents.
So suppose the problem at hand now is to actually build
中文字幕
something like the froshims website and let students register and then see
who is registered.
中文字幕
Well, back in my day, I fairly lazily, for lack of technical know-how,
just emailed the registrations to the proctor or the RA who was
中文字幕
managing the intramural sports program.
But I-- they later started putting it in CSV files.
中文字幕
Suppose now, version 3, 20 years later, I want to store in an actual database.
How can I actually do that and then see the results?
中文字幕
Well, let me go into the IDE again and open up,
for instance, a New File that I'll go ahead and call lecture.py.
中文字幕
And suppose I just want to write a simple Python program via which
to select data from a database.
中文字幕
So it turns out I can do a few things here.
First of all, let me go ahead and do, let's say, from CS50,
中文字幕
I previously have done things like import get_string and get_int
and so forth.
中文字幕
It turns out that the CS50 library for Python also supports SQL.
And it's going to give us a function called
中文字幕
EXECUTE that will let you execute any SQL command, but in Python code.
So instead of pulling up SQLite3 via my own hands
中文字幕
or going to a graphical user interface phpLiteAdmin,
I can write code that talks directly to froshims.db,
中文字幕
and eliminate all of those tools altogether, and just now write code.
So how do I do this?
中文字幕
I'm going to declare a variable called db for Database.
So I could call it anything I want.
中文字幕
And I'm going to go ahead and call this SQL function.
And I'm going to pass in a somewhat funky looking string as an argument,
中文字幕
but it's a standard convention, to say what
database technology do you want to use?
中文字幕
Then you do colon, slash, slash, slash-- so it's three slashes, not
the usual two in a URL.
中文字幕
And I'm going to specify froshims.db.
This now will give me a Python variable called
中文字幕
database that is kind of like a portal, if you will, into that database
file that I can send SELECTs, and INSERTs, and DELETEs, and UPDATEs to.
中文字幕
How do I do this?
Well, if at the end of the day, I want to execute
中文字幕
the equivalent of SELECT star from registrants, how do I do that?
Well, I'm just in a text editor, right?
中文字幕
This is CS50 IDE.
I'm just typing text.
中文字幕
Moreover, I'm typing text in a Python file, and this is not Python.
And indeed, the IDE has this little red x saying, mm-mm, can't do this.
中文字幕
But I could pass SQL code as an input to a Python function
and let that function talk to the database.
中文字幕
And indeed, that's what we're going to get here from CS50's library.
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
You know what?
Access the database and EXECUTE the following SQL code,
中文字幕
quote unquote, "that" close parentheses.
Now, what is select return by convention?
中文字幕
What should it return?
Well, in SQLite3, we just saw a pretty text-based table
中文字幕
with lines and slashes that looked like a table, but was just text.
phpLiteAdmin, we actually saw HTML tables when I browsed the database.
中文字幕
And I proposed verbally, a bit ago that, you know what?
If I were to get back all of this data in code, what data type
中文字幕
would I like it to me as?
Rows.
中文字幕
I want rows from a table.
Show me all the students who've registered.
中文字幕
What data structure in Python seems apt?
List.
中文字幕
Yeah, just a list, right?
A list that's ordered from first row to last row.
中文字幕
So we'll call that a list or an array, back in the day of C. So you know what?
I'm going to assume that's correct.
中文字幕
And if I read the documentation, I would see that it's correct.
CS50's EXECUTE function, if you select, returns to you a list of rows.
中文字幕
It might have 0 rows if there are no matches.
But it might have 1,000 rows if there are lots of matches.
中文字幕
I'm going to store those results, wherever they are, in my rows array.
Now, suppose I want to print out who has registered in my database
中文字幕
from whatever froshims website exists.
I'm assuming students have registered on the web.
中文字幕
Now I'm just the proctor or the RA who's actually now
trying to manipulate the data and do something with it.
中文字幕
So what can I do?
Well, for row in rows, what do I want to do?
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and just print out that so-and-so registered.
So so-and-so registered.
中文字幕
Well, how do I plug in so-and-so?
Well, there are a few ways to do this.
中文字幕
And let's see.
First of all, I could use my placeholder syntax for print.
中文字幕
And then, I want to print out the row.
But what do I want from that row?
中文字幕
What columns are in any row in this database?
ID and name and dorm and phone and sports.
中文字幕
Well, it turns out, those are going to be handed to you as Python dictionaries
or dict structures.
中文字幕
So I can just say row quote unquote, 'name' here.
And I'll use single quotes just to make more clear what's going on here.
中文字幕
And then I need to make one fix.
How do I--
中文字幕
F.
--F for Format string.
中文字幕
So it looks a little cryptic.
But this is just Python stuff now.
中文字幕
The only thing that's new is SQL.
But if we stipulate that SQL, when using this execute function
中文字幕
is just going to hand you all a list of rows, each of which
is a dictionary so that you can get at this column or this column--
中文字幕
ID, or name, or dorm--
this would seem to be now a nice convergence of this week--
中文字幕
now, with the past couple of weeks.
So let me go ahead and save this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and View my Console, so I have a Terminal window.
And let me go ahead and run Python of lecture.py.
中文字幕
And in just a moment, if I cross my fingers,
I should hopefully see who has registered.
中文字幕
Amazing.
I've seen who's registered.
中文字幕
Now there's one line of output that I didn't expect, which is just this one.
This is the library just being pedagogically helpful.
中文字幕
It's showing me every command that I sent to the database.
But you'll see that so-and-so has registered.
中文字幕
So this is kind of interesting.
It's kind of a stupid program, right?
中文字幕
Because most proctors aren't going to be hacking
froshims by using a terminal window and running Python scripts.
中文字幕
They're probably going to want to do this by a web page
and actually see who is registered.
中文字幕
But if we have the ability in Python code to do this, like,
iteration, what could I do instead of just printing to the screen?
中文字幕
What could I print out per last week and per the past problems set?
I could print out HTML, right?
中文字幕
Like, each of the students who register, kind of
feels like an opportunity for an unordered list
中文字幕
or an ordered list or a table or whatever.
You can now generate HTML.
中文字幕
So let me do this.
Let me actually go into an example I've made in advance.
中文字幕
What if I went ahead and opened up layout.html.
Here is a simple layout for a web application using Flask.
中文字幕
For those unfamiliar, this is mostly HTML
plus a technology called Jinja, which is a web-based technology for generating
中文字幕
websites dynamically.
The body of this page is clearly what's of interest.
中文字幕
And you know what?
I bet I could do some logic right in there.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and Create, let's say, a New File.
中文字幕
Let's call this application.py.
I'm going to go ahead and, just for time's sake,
中文字幕
do a little bit of copy-paste to save myself some keystrokes.
So here's a very simple web app.
中文字幕
And this is going to be my to-do.
So if I go in here to templates, let me open up index.html--
中文字幕
and let me go head into here.
So long story short--
中文字幕
here's where we're going with this.
What if I instead generate an unordered list using code from last week,
中文字幕
but I use my for loop here inside of my web app
instead of actually just with a simple lecture.py file.
中文字幕
Well, recall that I could do something like this.
I can have a Jinja loop.
中文字幕
So I could say something like for row in rows.
And then, down here, I can preemptively say something
中文字幕
like andfor, which is our weird syntax from last week.
And then, in here, I can just do a list item.
中文字幕
And then, if I want to show who registered, what do I type here?
Something in between these curly braces if each row represents a registrant?
中文字幕
Row.
Row name registered.
中文字幕
I can just do something like this.
So same idea, I'm just wrapping it with a little bit of HTML.
中文字幕
Now let me go to my application.py file because I'm
going to have to fill in some blanks.
中文字幕
And let me see, how can I do this?
Well, ultimately, I want to return the result of rendering
中文字幕
a template called index.html.
For families unfamiliar, this is just a line of code
中文字幕
that says go show that file to the user.
But I don't want to just show them the file as-is.
中文字幕
But let's at least get this set up.
I'm worried that it might not work yet because I need to get the actual data.
中文字幕
So how can I get all of the rows for my registrants?
Well, I can do rows gets db.execute.
中文字幕
And I can go ahead and select star from registrants and store that in there.
This file is called froshims.db that I created earlier.
中文字幕
And everything else is just Flask stuff from last week.
Nothing else is new.
中文字幕
The only thing that's new is this line here,
this line here, and now this line here where
中文字幕
I'm using SQL inside of a Python call by passing
it is an argument to a function called EXECUTE.
中文字幕
How do I pass the rows to index.html?
Yeah, like rows equals rows is the convention we've adopted.
中文字幕
You call it anything you want, x equals y,
but this is a little more straightforward.
中文字幕
So this is saying, hey, database, get me all of the rows from my registrants,
and then render the template index.html, and pass in these rows.
中文字幕
And now, if I hold my breath and run flask run, no syntax errors.
If I go ahead and visit this here and open--
中文字幕
dammit-- the tab, I see an internal server error.
So teachable moment, families.
中文字幕
Let's go back into that browser window here and see what happened.
OK.
中文字幕
Template syntax error-- so pretty stupid mistake.
It looks like I expected a square bracket instead of a curly brace.
中文字幕
That's fixable.
Let me go into index.html.
中文字幕
And oh, I didn't finish my thought.
So that's some of the frustrations of programming for those
中文字幕
who are seeing this for the first time.
Let me save that.
中文字幕
Let me go back to the browser here, and we'll just reload.
And oh my god, voila, now I have a web page
中文字幕
via which you can see who has registered.
But you know what?
中文字幕
We can make this more powerful.
Recall that we've been playing with HTTP for some time.
中文字幕
And if this is the URL I'm accessing, recall
that we played around with reimplementing search functionality.
中文字幕
Well, what if I want to support search such that I can just visit q
equals and then search for people named, say, Brian
中文字幕
and see how many Brians are registered.
Could we add support for something like this?
中文字幕
Well, maybe.
Let me go back into the IDE, into application.py.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and say something like this.
q equals request.args get q to see if anything is actually there.
中文字幕
And then let me go ahead and do this.
SELECT star FROM registrants WHERE--
中文字幕
let me see-- q where what?
NAME equals q.
中文字幕
But I need a placeholder.
So maybe I should do this.
中文字幕
And as soon as I do this, I need a what?
F for a format string.
中文字幕
So I could just create, on the fly, a SQL command
that plugs in the value of q between those curly
中文字幕
braces to express the logic of select all
of the registrants whose names equal Brian or Veronica
中文字幕
or whoever's name I typed in.
Let me go back to the browser here.
中文字幕
Let me go over and do something like this now.
Question mark q equals Brian-- cross my fingers as before.
中文字幕
Dammit.
OK.
中文字幕
And what did I do wrong here?
What did I do wrong here?
中文字幕
This is subtle.
And we're seeing it for the first time.
中文字幕
It thinks there's a column called Brian.
But why would it think that?
中文字幕
Well, what I've effectively done is sent in this.
Brian is not a keyword in SQL.
中文字幕
And because it's an actual string that I'm comparing against,
what I really need to be doing is this.
中文字幕
Otherwise, SQLite is going to think it's like the name of a column or something
I pre-created so we have to fix this.
中文字幕
But that's OK.
I can put the quotes there.
中文字幕
But I should probably put the q there in quotes.
Let's save this, go back to the browser, reload.
中文字幕
And there we go.
Now we have functionality for Brian.
中文字幕
And so with this basic building block, what have we done?
Well, in SQL, we have several commands at our disposal--
中文字幕
creating a table, which frankly gets tedious by typing it out.
I myself tend to use and recommend phpLiteAdmin just to create your table
中文字幕
and get it going.
But then you can certainly manually, with SQLite3 or phpLiteAdmin INSERT,
中文字幕
or UPDATE, or DELETE, or SELECT information
once it's actually in the database.
中文字幕
And that's pretty powerful.
But once you do that, you can now use that same new syntax, that new language
中文字幕
SQL, passing it in as an input with a "string" to our EXECUTE function,
and now start pulling any data you want from your database.
中文字幕
Last week, with CSV files, if you wanted to do this,
you'd have to open the CSV file, use a for loop to iterate over it,
中文字幕
look over every column and row for your data, then pass it in.
And that's fine.
中文字幕
That's correct.
That's not bad.
中文字幕
But it's tedious.
And you're reinventing the wheel again and again.
中文字幕
And there's no filtration built in as there is to SQL itself.
So you now have a more sophisticated tool
中文字幕
in your toolkit so to speak with which to solve that same kind of problem.
Any questions then on this technique?
中文字幕
All right.
Well, let's look at a bigger database and see where we can go with this?
中文字幕
So if you go on the course's website, you'll
see a larger database that's actually available in multiple formats, SQLite,
中文字幕
which we'll see in a moment, but also Google Spreadsheets.
Because frankly, it's a lot more pleasant to look
中文字幕
at your rows and columns in a GUI than it is, necessarily,
with the file itself.
中文字幕
So this happens to be a free and open source sample database.
Like, some guy, years ago, took his actual iTunes database--
中文字幕
all the music he'd ever bought, he wrote a program
to like analyze Apple's file format in iTunes
中文字幕
and extract all of the data that seemed to be stored about him,
I think was the story, and just made it publicly available as a sample
中文字幕
database for students and teachers to just use to manipulate data.
But what's interesting is that this database
中文字幕
demonstrates some other principles that we really haven't touched on.
For instance, if I were to store, again and again,
中文字幕
all of these students who are registering for froshims,
what do you start to see in certain fields?
中文字幕
Well, I was a little lazy, and I didn't bother typing in everyone's dorm.
But suppose that hundreds of students have registered for froshims.
中文字幕
A lot of them are going to be from Matthews, some from Pennypacker,
some from Candaday, some from Weld, and bunches of other buildings on campus.
中文字幕
It starts to get a little ridiculous when
you see Matthews, Matthews, Matthews, Matthews,
中文字幕
Matthews-- like, 100 or more times.
If there are 1,600 freshmen, there are a lot of kids in Matthews.
中文字幕
That's a lot of bytes to store M-A-T-T-H-E-W--
I don't know.
中文字幕
It's not important.
Doesn't matter how it's spelled.
中文字幕
That's a lot of bytes to actually store in your database again and again
and again.
中文字幕
It feels like there should be an opportunity
to factor out the commonalities.
中文字幕
And what humans do with databases is, once they recognize a recurring
pattern of data, same darn strings again and again and again, you know what?
中文字幕
Rather than use-- now it matters--
M-A-T-T-H-E-W-S-- which is 8 bytes.
中文字幕
Or P-E-N-N-Y-P-A-C-K-E-R, which is 11, then we have a lot of bytes being used
again and again and again to store all of these dorms.
中文字幕
You know what?
What's better than 11 bytes or 8 bytes?
中文字幕
Let's just use an int, or let's even use a small int--
2 bytes or 4 bytes to represent dorms.
中文字幕
So instead of storing Matthews, let's just store the number 10.
And instead of Penny Packer, lets just store the number 11, thereby,
中文字幕
using some bytes, but fewer and, therefore,
saving bytes in the long run.
中文字幕
And so with this database demonstrates is exactly that principle.
Certainly, when it comes to music, where artists have multiple albums
中文字幕
and artists have multiple songs, it's probably
a little silly in a musical database to store the name of the album
中文字幕
again and again and again and again for all 10 or 12
or 20 tracks or songs on that particular album.
中文字幕
So what this person did was this.
Notice here, we have a whole bunch of sheets.
中文字幕
Or in database-speak, these would be tables.
And notice that these tables have columns.
中文字幕
And notice that these columns are album ID,
in the album table, album ID and title.
中文字幕
But notice what he did very cleverly with this field, artist ID.
Artists or singers have lots of songs to their name, eventually.
中文字幕
And so he's assigned each of them unique value,
or Apple did, in iTunes underneath the hood.
中文字幕
So how do I know what this artist's name is?
How would you figure this out?
中文字幕
It's not that interesting to us humans do know, ooh, artist ID number 2.
This is just-- what's that?
中文字幕
You need another table with artists.
Yeah.
中文字幕
We need another table with artists, which is right over here.
So let me go ahead and look there.
中文字幕
So if I want to see-- let's see, "Let there be rock," artist number 1.
Let's go to the artists table.
中文字幕
And turns out, AC/DC, the band is who created that.
Now we've added a step here, which maybe is costing us a little bit of time.
中文字幕
But it's going to save a space in the long run if I'm not storing long
artist's names-- although, AC/DC isn't terribly long--
中文字幕
again and again and again.
Now, which is better?
中文字幕
Well, it's a trade-off.
Are you more comfortable wasting space and storing everything together?
中文字幕
Or do you prefer to save space and just spend a little more time
joining the data back together?
中文字幕
But it's going to be really annoying if, now,
if I want to make a website that shows me the names of the songs
中文字幕
that I have in a database and the artists for them,
let alone the albums, and more of that, the titles of the tracks, and so forth.
中文字幕
It feels like that's three queries, right?
Like SELECT the album, SELECT the artist, SELECT the titles--
中文字幕
but no.
With SQL, you can collapse that altogether.
中文字幕
Because notice, in this table here, artist,
there is a column called Artist ID that's numbers.
中文字幕
And notice, if you kind of picture this, it's
like finger tips here-- let's propose metaphorically--
中文字幕
represent the artist ID.
If I go into album now, notice that we have album ID and title,
中文字幕
but we also have artist ID.
And so if you imagine these two tables sharing this common column, what if we
中文字幕
kind of stitch them together like this, lining up one
on the left, the other on the right, thereby reconstructing
中文字幕
all of the information and duplicating it as
needed so that I get back just the album and the title and the artist.
中文字幕
Well, how can express that?
Well, let me go ahead into CS50 IDE where I have a copy of this file.
中文字幕
Let me close all of my tabs from earlier go into this file called lecture.db.
And in lecture.db, in phpLiteAdmin, we'll see all of those same tables.
中文字幕
And I literally just imported it into a SQLite.
You'll see all of these same tables.
中文字幕
We can browse album just as before.
And we just see a different format for the same data.
中文字幕
It's the same data from the Google Spreadsheet,
which is just more user-friendly.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and do this.
I could, of course, SELECT star from album
中文字幕
Where our artist ID equals 1 to get back all of AC/DC's albums.
And indeed, here, I have two.
中文字幕
They have For those about to rock, We salute you, and Let there be rock.
They have two.
中文字幕
But notice, the rows I got back contain only what information?
Album ID title, and artist ID.
中文字幕
I just know, as a human, that oh, these are AC/DC's albums.
But what if I want to know, well, OK, I see that artist ID is 1.
中文字幕
So all right, well, let me open another tab here.
And now let me SELECT star from artist WHERE artist ID equals 1.
中文字幕
And so if I want to learn something about that artist-- let me go ahead
and Zoom Out, click Go, and OK-- now I get AC/DC.
中文字幕
Well, this is great.
Now I have to results, two sets of rows.
中文字幕
This is stupid.
Now I'm just creating work for myself by having two return values.
中文字幕
I could call db EXECUTE twice.
But there's a better way.
中文字幕
It turns out, SQL allows you to join tables just using SQL itself.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and SELECT star FROM album,
but also FROM artist WHERE Album.Artistid--
中文字幕
let me scroll to the right--
equals Artist.Artistid.
中文字幕
So notice I'm saying select everything from two tables,
but only do so where the album tables, artist ID
中文字幕
column has the same value as the artist tables artist ID column.
That's kind of the stitching, metaphorically, of my fingers
中文字幕
together, looking for that common column.
If I go ahead and click Go, wow, look at what I've just constructed.
中文字幕
It's a lot of information, but I have album ID and title,
I have artists ID still, but I have the name of that artist altogether.
中文字幕
So if you now let your mind wander back to the Python code,
oh, I could now get a whole bunch of rows containing
中文字幕
everything I care about all at once.
I don't need two select queries.
中文字幕
I can join these tables in this way.
And I use join very deliberately.
中文字幕
It turns out that there's another way to express this same thing.
Instead of using that comma syntax I did, you might see as well this,
中文字幕
Select star From Artist JOIN Album ON Artist.Artistid equals--
let me scroll over--
中文字幕
Album.Artistid.
This is going to have the exact same effect,
中文字幕
but you might just find that it reads a little more intuitively to you.
Select everything from the result of joining these two tables.
中文字幕
How do you want to join them?
Well, join them on this equaling that--
中文字幕
just another way of expressing the same idea.
And if I click Go, I get back the same information.
中文字幕
So ultimately, with JOINs do we have the ability to reassemble data.
So on the one hand, it's just good practice to normalize your database.
中文字幕
Identify columns that have lots and lots and lots of redundancy, and only
store that information once.
中文字幕
For instance, CS50 Finance, if you're supporting
many different users, every time Malan or Brian or Veronica buys a stock,
中文字幕
feels like it would be a little silly to store Malan
or Brian or Veronica along with Netflix, the symbol, and the number of shares
中文字幕
one of us bought.
Because Malan, Malan, Malan, Malan is going
中文字幕
to appear all throughout the database.
And what if I change my username or my name or someone gets married
中文字幕
and, therefore, it changes?
Like, why do you create that messiness for yourself?
中文字幕
Instead, give Brian and Veronica and me and everyone else a unique ID.
And when they buy something, just store their user ID or customer ID
中文字幕
or however you want to think about it, just like with album ID and artist ID.
And so normalizing a database is all about finding those commonalities
中文字幕
and moving the data into its own table.
And if you care about rejoining it, just use
中文字幕
SQL to reconstruct that view of the data, so to speak.
So what else can we do here as well?
中文字幕
It turns out that there is in SQL, not just primary keys,
but there are unique constraints in some databases where you can specify,
中文字幕
this isn't my primary key, but I want it to be unique.
You can specify that something should be indexed.
中文字幕
So it turns out that, if you just know there's a field in your database
that you want to be able to search on very efficiently,
中文字幕
you can index it in advance.
And you'll see or be able to do this if you'd like for final projects
中文字幕
or even for the next problem set if you'd like.
But what this enables are queries like this.
中文字幕
If I want to go ahead and search for, for instance--
what would be a good example?
中文字幕
Rock.
I'm interested in rock.
中文字幕
So if I want to go into My SQL tab here.
I could say something like this.
中文字幕
SELECT star FROM Album WHERE Name not equals,
but where name is LIKE and then I'm going to say 'Rock.'
中文字幕
But if I want any number of characters to come before that word,
I can use a percent sign.
中文字幕
And if any number of characters after, I can use a percent sign.
These are like wildcards.
中文字幕
In most languages, you would use star.
In SQL, you use percent signs.
中文字幕
But it means the same thing.
And if I go ahead and say go, now I get back--
中文字幕
oh, I get the got wrong lecture, album, oh, title I think is what I wanted.
Let me try that again, sorry--
中文字幕
WHERE Title LIKE 'Rock'--
let me go ahead and click Go.
中文字幕
And voila, here are all of the albums in the database that
have the word rock in them.
中文字幕
Now, as an aside, this table has a lot of more albums in it.
And frankly, it's small enough though.
中文字幕
It has hundreds of rows, maybe a few thousand rows.
None of us humans are really going to notice how slow linear search is.
中文字幕
But if you start having thousands of rows, tens of thousands
of rows, millions of rows, not having an index
中文字幕
means that searching for something like rock is going to start at the top
and search every darn field all the way to the bottom, big O of n.
中文字幕
If you instead tell the database, I know I'm
going to be searching on this column a lot, please index it for me,
中文字幕
here comes the secret sauce.
SQLite, Oracle, Microsoft Access, and so forth, they
中文字幕
will, using their own intellectual property,
build up some fancy data structures-- trees, or hash tables,
中文字幕
or whatever in memory, store the data for you invisibly in that format
so that, when you do ask for a question like, show me all the albums like rock,
中文字幕
they can answer you in much faster time than linear.
And that too is what you get with SQL that you don't get with CSVs.
中文字幕
CSVs are, by nature, only linear.
So we can do better.
中文字幕
But you, the programmer, have to help the database
and actually give it those hints, not just the types,
中文字幕
but also hints like this.
And as an aside, there's also the notion of foreign keys
中文字幕
where, if you really want to lock things down, you can specify that,
if you ever see in album ID in another table,
中文字幕
if it's a primary key in the album table,
by definition, in the other table, it's going to be called a foreign key.
中文字幕
Because it doesn't really belong there, but it's
referencing a column elsewhere.
中文字幕
So there's a lot more technology and vocabulary.
And you're welcome to dive in deeper.
中文字幕
And odds are, many of you will for final projects,
by nature of wanting certain features, among them, even
中文字幕
the ones we've seen like auto incrementing and not null.
As an aside too, SQL even has functions.
中文字幕
And for data scientists and statisticians
it's super useful to be able to just do math and summaries of data right
中文字幕
within SQL without ever writing Python code or R or anything else.
Built into a SQLite and other databases are
中文字幕
functions like this for average, counting things, getting
the min, max, sum, and so forth--
中文字幕
all of that you get for free with a lot of databases.
All it takes in the context of Python is a line like this.
中文字幕
But, but, but, but, but there are some problems.
And let's end by taking a look at two fundamental problems and threats that
中文字幕
are too often underappreciated.
And in fact, we have to fix a very serious vulnerability that I introduced
中文字幕
into my very own code earlier.
But first, the so-called race condition.
中文字幕
In survey-- or rather, let's see--
suppose that we think back at the very start of the semester, most of you
中文字幕
signed up for a GitHub account for the very first time.
And you went to github.com/signup.
中文字幕
For those unfamiliar, GitHub is a website
where you can save and store programming code that you've written
中文字幕
and want to collaborate with others on.
And you chose a username.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and try choosing a username like, say, jharvard
for John Harvard.
中文字幕
Notice that the website immediately said the user name is taken.
All right, that's useful.
中文字幕
And you can probably guess how this is done-- maybe a little JavaScript,
using AJAX, talking to the server, getting the response,
中文字幕
changing the HTML or the CSS or whatever.
Might take some time to wire all that together.
中文字幕
But that's probably what's going on.
So let me try a really long random username that is not taken.
中文字幕
Hey, it's available.
But probably is not a good thing that I'm streaming this on the internet.
中文字幕
Because if I wait long enough, I bet someone could, for playful reasons,
just sign up for this, let alone anyone in this room.
中文字幕
But you've just told me it's available.
So good.
中文字幕
I'm really excited.
I've got my username.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and type in my email address,
malan@harvard.edu, my password, 12345-- take a few moments there.
中文字幕
Verify my account and so forth.
And I click Submit.
中文字幕
Suppose that I'm told, momentarily, sorry, that username has been taken.
Could that happen?
中文字幕
Yeah, if any of you were trying to mess with me right now,
you would have signed up for that username and beaten me to the punch
中文字幕
so that when I hit Join, I get an error.
That's the definition of a race condition where two people or two users
中文字幕
or two computers or two threads--
if we really roll back to our discussion of threads in Scratch--
中文字幕
are trying to do the same thing at roughly the same time.
And if those two things, threads or humans,
中文字幕
check the state of a variable, which is a fancy way of saying
is the username available, they both get back answers.
中文字幕
But then some number of split seconds later,
then they make a decision based on that information, there is a window of time,
中文字幕
either split seconds or even seconds or minutes,
where the state of that variable could, of course, change.
中文字幕
So if you two, literally, right now on your laptop,
typed that very long username, all of us would probably be told, green light,
中文字幕
it's available.
But only one of us is actually going to get it.
中文字幕
And that's because of a race condition.
Literally, all of us might be racing to sign up for that value.
中文字幕
And it's when state can change in between things happening.
This is a bad thing because it makes your data
中文字幕
vulnerable to changes by someone you don't necessarily intend.
Or if the database isn't smart, you might
中文字幕
be able to do especially bad things.
ATMs are a canonical example of this.
中文字幕
If you had a malicious adversary trying to log into two bank accounts at once
or two physical machines at once, either with two cards or two accounts and two
中文字幕
laptops, you could imagine both of them trying to deduct, like,
$100 from the same account instantly.
中文字幕
Because imagine a poorly-implemented bank website.
It checks the account balance of the user logged in.
中文字幕
Do you have $100?
If the answer is yes, maybe both websites are going to say yes,
中文字幕
you may deduct $100.
You hit enter and voila, you deduct $100.
中文字幕
The user gets it somehow because it's transferred to some other account.
But the bank thinks it only did that once, deducts $100,
中文字幕
but you've just walked away with $200 because you made a decision based
on the same answer in two different threads
中文字幕
or two different programs or two different computers.
So long story short, this can happen even in the real world.
中文字幕
An example I was taught by my advisor years ago was this.
Suppose you and your roommates have a little dorm fridge.
中文字幕
And you're in the habit, of course, of drinking a lot of milk.
And so the fridge has run out of milk.
中文字幕
And you come home, the first roommate after classes.
And you realize, oh, I really need a drink of milk.
中文字幕
And so you check the fridge.
There's nothing there.
中文字幕
So you close the fridge, and you walk into the square, go to CVS,
and get in line to buy some milk.
中文字幕
Meanwhile, your roommate comes home.
Also, they really need a drink of milk.
中文字幕
And so they check the state of the variable.
Argh, no milk.
中文字幕
Close the fridge, and then walk to like Tommy's Convenience or some other place
nearby and get in line for some milk.
中文字幕
You of course, then both get home eventually.
And what happens now?
中文字幕
Dammit, now you have twice as much milk.
And milk goes bad quickly.
中文字幕
So now this is a problem, a very bad problem.
You have twice as much milk as you could possibly drink.
中文字幕
But what's the origin of that problem fundamentally?
You're out of something.
中文字幕
You're out of something, but--
You need it.
中文字幕
--you need it.
But why did I end up with two?
中文字幕
There's no flag.
There's no flag, right?
中文字幕
There's no indication.
There's no sharing of state.
中文字幕
You both inspected the value of the variable,
made a decision independently on it.
中文字幕
But the state of that variable changed on one of you.
Because when one of you came home, the later person, damn, like,
中文字幕
the milk has already been refilled.
So how do you solve this?
中文字幕
In the real world, how could you avoid this problem?
You just, one, never do errands for your roommate.
中文字幕
The magnet you put on the refrigerator says get this.
Mag-- yes.
中文字幕
A shopping list, right-- gone for milk--
Arrested Development.
中文字幕
Always leave a note, right?
You could convey that information.
中文字幕
You could more dramatically lock the refrigerator, right?
Padlock the thing, and so your roommate can't
中文字幕
inspect the state of the refrigerator while you are gone, therefore,
not making us vulnerable to this.
中文字幕
And I use the word lock deliberately because,
in databases, that's how they solve this.
中文字幕
There is a feature in databases called locks.
Or fancier versions of this are called transactions,
中文字幕
whereby, you can guarantee something called atomicity,
where atomicity means you can do multiple things back to back to back
中文字幕
without getting interrupted.
So in the case of a bank, it is possible, with SQL, using slightly
中文字幕
fancier syntax that we won't dive into today to solve this problem by saying,
you know what?
中文字幕
Begin the following transaction.
Check the state of the bank account, deduct this amount of money,
中文字幕
and now commit the results.
And while I'm doing that, lock everyone else out.
中文字幕
Don't let any other customer or any other user
do exactly that information that touches the same data until I am done.
中文字幕
Long story short-- you pay a price, perhaps.
You're literally preventing your roommate from accessing the fridge,
中文字幕
and that's annoying.
Or you're preventing other customers from doing transactions.
中文字幕
So hopefully the computer is fast at this, and your fast at shopping.
But you've at least ensured that you have atomicity.
中文字幕
No operation can get inserted into your sequence of operations
as by your roommate or some other computer or thread.
中文字幕
So that's a problem with databases that we're only going to skirt over.
And GitHub might solve this, how?
中文字幕
Well, by just not caring, potentially.
I don't know what's going to happen if multiple of us try.
中文字幕
I'm guessing they will just give n minus 1 of us an error message saying, sorry,
that username is no longer available.
中文字幕
Think about this.
If you've ever bought airline tickets, this
中文字幕
is a solved problem in that industry.
That would be really annoying.
中文字幕
If you just spent an hour of stressful price-hunting
for a good airplane ticket, you start checking out
中文字幕
after adding it to your shopping cart.
And five minutes later, after your name and email address and credit card
中文字幕
number, the ticket is gone.
So what do airlines do?
中文字幕
They often give you a five-minute window.
And some of the fancier websites show you the clock saying,
中文字幕
we guarantee this for the next five minutes.
Hotels might do this too where they locked the refrigerator for you
中文字幕
by somehow altering the database to say, mm-mm.
No one else can buy this ticket or this room for the next five minutes,
中文字幕
much like the note or the padlock.
So those kinds of things are all around us.
中文字幕
But let's look at one final example that's the worst threat of all is this.
Previously, I allowed myself to search by name.
中文字幕
So q equals Brian or q equals David or Veronica or the like.
And what did I do with that information?
中文字幕
Well, if we go back into the IDE and actually look
at that file in application.py, I simply formatted it using an F string
中文字幕
inside of this SQL string.
But what if my users were a little bit malicious?
中文字幕
And suppose that someone doesn't want to just search for Brian.
But you know what?
中文字幕
Suppose they do something like, my query is DELETE FROM registrants WHERE--
sorry Brian-- NAME equals Brian--
中文字幕
something like this.
Now, this is not valid at the moment, because this string,
中文字幕
while I'm certainly allowed to type it in,
is going to get plugged into my code, but in the wrong place logically.
中文字幕
Like, I'm going to look for someone's name called "DELETE FROM registrants
WHERE name equals Brian," which is just nonsensical.
中文字幕
It will return 0 results.
But what if I do something like this where I say,
中文字幕
Brian or DELETE from registrants where I finish
the thought that the programmer had and then start my own new thought.
中文字幕
Or another way of doing this is to use special syntax semicolon, something
like this.
中文字幕
Long story short, I could contrive a human malicious input that
finishes the programmer's thought and returns zero rows, but by the way,
中文字幕
also sneaks one additional rogue query into the database.
This is what's known as a SQL injection attack.
中文字幕
And if you naively and very, very, very badly and incorrectly write code like I
did-- don't ever do this--
中文字幕
you will be vulnerable to exactly this attack
because you are blindly plugging in the user's input to a string
中文字幕
that you are then passing to a database.
This is a fundamental flaw in lots of applications, lots of languages
中文字幕
where you have to distrust your users.
It doesn't matter if it's for just students on campus
中文字幕
or it's just for you and your friends.
Never ever, ever trust users' input because either someone's
中文字幕
going to mistype something and something is going to go awry,
or you're going to have a bad apple trying
中文字幕
to hack into your website or your application
by trying these kinds of commands.
中文字幕
And you have to always write code defensively.
So how to do this?
中文字幕
There are a bunch of ways.
But it turns out that, what's dangerous about something
中文字幕
like I just typed in is that it's the semicolon, for instance,
and that's the quote marks over "elsewhere."
中文字幕
So the safest thing to do is, no matter what the user types in, escape things.
You can use special syntax.
中文字幕
We saw this in C-- generally, putting a backslash in front of something means,
don't let it have its default behavior.
中文字幕
Instead, treat it specially.
So you could use special code in Python that
中文字幕
just says remove any bad characters, or replace things.
Frankly, you've probably been to a website where you've been told,
中文字幕
sorry, you can't use that character in your password.
Or sorry, you can't use that in your username.
中文字幕
That's just dumb.
Like, that is the lazy approach to this.
中文字幕
There is no reason to prevent users from typing
any characters into their keyboard for their password and maybe even
中文字幕
their username.
That's kind of a lazy way of defending against this by saying,
中文字幕
mm-mm, I don't trust any percent sign, any semicolons,
any dashes, any apostrophes.
中文字幕
Rather, just escape things.
But it's silly for all of us in this room
中文字幕
to write our own code for scaping users' input or scrubbing it, as it's called,
or sanitizing it, as it's called-- same things.
中文字幕
Why don't we just use a library?
Now, there are many libraries out there.
中文字幕
The one that we're using at the moment is CS50's.
And the EXECUTE function does this for us.
中文字幕
Instead of using F strings, which you should not use like this.
You should instead do this.
中文字幕
If you want to plug in a placeholder value to a SQL query,
you literally use a standard convention, that we have adopted too,
中文字幕
where you just put in a variable's name, but with a colon in front of it.
And it can be anything.
中文字幕
It can be q.
It can be x.
中文字幕
It doesn't matter.
But you want to just plug in some value there.
中文字幕
So I'm going to call it name, by convention.
Then you close your quote and finish your thought.
中文字幕
And then you go ahead and pass in the actual value, name equals q.
And now you have constructed, dynamically,
中文字幕
a SQL string with a place holder that is not
Python's own curly brace placeholder.
中文字幕
This is a special SQL convention where you say plug in value here.
What value?
中文字幕
We'll plug in this names value, q, whatever the human has typed in.
And what are execute function will do for you
中文字幕
is all of the fancy backslashing and all of the escaping
and will protect you from the user's data.
中文字幕
And this is how truly simple it is.
It doesn't have to be CS50's library.
中文字幕
This is ever so common in all languages, but too few people know about it
and use it.
中文字幕
And so half the time you read about some database getting hacked
or your data getting stolen, it is because
中文字幕
of a stupid oversight like that.
So just use libraries and escape users' input.
中文字幕
We can see this now more concretely.
All of the undergrads in the room have surely
中文字幕
logged into, either Yale's website or Harvard's website,
which looks a little something like this here.
中文字幕
You're prompted for your login name and your password,
or your Harvard key or the like.
中文字幕
Well, how does this take effect in real terms?
If I were to type in my email address--
中文字幕
but then weird syntax like this-- let's look at an example.
Quote "or" quote unquote "1" equals quote "1."
中文字幕
Notice it's not balanced.
It's missing a quote over here, missing a quote over here.
中文字幕
Because the presumption is that maybe Harvard is vulnerable to this.
I don't think they are.
中文字幕
But suppose that the code running Harvard key
and Harvard's login page looks a little something like this.
中文字幕
This is bad.
This is dangerous because they're just using f strings or format
中文字幕
strings, which are just going to blindly plug anything in there.
And so if you let the human type in something cryptic like that,
中文字幕
notice what has happened logically.
Where username equals me at example your email provider.com and password
中文字幕
equals quote unquote, so nothing, or 1 equals 1.
And why 1 equals 1?
中文字幕
If I go back, notice that there's a quote here and a quote here.
And the reason that I didn't finish my second quote here or my second quote
中文字幕
here is because I'm assuming, as a bad guy,
I think Harvard is just going to blindly plug my input
中文字幕
into a single quotes of their own.
Therefore, I can finish their thought nonsensically.
中文字幕
But notice, logically, what happens.
Select all users from the database where the user name is me at example email
中文字幕
provider and the password is nothing.
Or 1 equals 1.
中文字幕
Well, when does 1 equal 1?
Like, always.
中文字幕
So this will always return users from the database,
and presumably, therefore, let me log in as one of those users--
中文字幕
so incredibly simple to defend against this.
Just use placeholder syntax and distrust and sanitize users' input.
中文字幕
The syntax in SQL and the CS50 library is quite simply with that colon.
But in other libraries, it might be quite the same.
中文字幕
So now you are all, families and students alike,
inaugurated into the small class of folks
中文字幕
in the world who understand particularly geeky humor.
You might notice this meme that's gone around the internet for many years
中文字幕
now where someone either maliciously or humorously
decided to paint this over their license platelets.
中文字幕
Let's enhance.
Why would someone do this?
中文字幕
Scanners.
Scanners, yeah.
中文字幕
Tollbooths are going away, at least in the US.
And they instead have cameras or readers that are scanning the front of your car
中文字幕
and trying to optically do OCR, Optical Character Recognition,
on your license plate.
中文字幕
And the presumption here is, maybe in some municipality,
there's some badly written code where they just blindly plug
中文字幕
your license plate into their code.
And hopefully you finish the thought where ZU 0666--
中文字幕
whatever that is, it's part of the license plate--
but "semicolon drop database table dot dot dot."
中文字幕
And we didn't even look at that because DROP is pretty extreme.
It literally deletes a database itself.
中文字幕
But this is a nice way of getting off the hook from a total price.
And most canonical perhaps, XKCD is a very popular cartoon strip.
中文字幕
It's particularly geek-oriented.
And you'll perhaps understand this joke now as well among CS circles.
中文字幕
I can hear the laughter making its way through.
So from here on out, if you take nothing else away,
中文字幕
remember little Bobby Tables with pset.
Our final, will you actually implement CS50 Finance
中文字幕
and coalesce all these ideas.
Thank you so much to all of our families for joining.
中文字幕
And we will see you next time.